<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>An epistle to the faithfull necessary for all the children of God: especially in the s[o] dangerous dayes. Written by Maister Peter Viret in french, and englished by F.H. Esquier.</title>
            <title>Epistre envoyée aux fidèles conversans entre les chrestiens papistiques. English</title>
            <author>Viret, Pierre, 1511-1571.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1582</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 197 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 73 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A14464</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 24779</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S104301</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99840039</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99840039</idno>
            <idno type="VID">4510</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A14464)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 4510)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1613:02)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>An epistle to the faithfull necessary for all the children of God: especially in the s[o] dangerous dayes. Written by Maister Peter Viret in french, and englished by F.H. Esquier.</title>
                  <title>Epistre envoyée aux fidèles conversans entre les chrestiens papistiques. English</title>
                  <author>Viret, Pierre, 1511-1571.</author>
                  <author>F. H., Esquier.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[144] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>[By T. Dawson] for Tobie Smith, dwelling in Paules church-yard, at the signe of the Crane,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Imprinted at London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1582.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>A translation of: Viret, Pierre.  Epistre envoyée aux fidèles conversans entre les chrestiens papistiques.</note>
                  <note>Printer's name from STC.</note>
                  <note>Advocates withdrawal as an alternative to participation in a society dominated by Roman Catholic precepts and practices.--NUC Pre-1956.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: [par.] 2[par.]⁴ A-G H⁴.</note>
                  <note>Some pages stained.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Catholic Church --  Controversial literature --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Reformed Church --  Controversial literature --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-12</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-12</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-02</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-02</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:4510:1"/>
            <p>¶ <hi>An Epiſtle to the</hi> Faithfull, neceſſary for all the children of God: eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <hi>cially in theſe dange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous dayes.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Written by Maiſter Peter Viret in French, and engli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed by <hi>F. H. E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſquier.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g> 
               <hi>Imprinted at</hi> London for Tobie Smith, dwelling in Paules Church<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <hi>yard, at the ſigne of the Crane.</hi> 1582.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:4510:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:4510:2"/>
            <head>The Epistle Dedicatory.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">H</seg>Auing long ſince peruſed a Treatiſe, written in French by M. Peter Vyret, whiche was dedicated by him, to the faythfull: and hauing for my priuate exerciſe tra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſlated the ſame, I little thought to haue ſent it abroade, but ſhewing it to ſome god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, whoſe iudgements I craued, both of the matter, &amp; tra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſlatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, they doubted not to giue great commendation of the one, and it plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed them to ſet downe their allowance of the other, and withall perſwaded me, the matter to be very profitable, for theſe our times, &amp; that by many reaſons: whereupon I became ſo encouraged, as (conſidering the argument to be ſo apt and fit for this age) I would not keepe back this ſo fruitfull a treatiſe from the viewe of my countrie men, but haue ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uentured to publiſh the ſame in engliſh, how rudely ſoeuer it be tranſlated. And nowe (Madam) hauing beene long debtor to your Ladyſhippe, for your manye honourable fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uours extended towardes me, and hauing long deſired to yeeld ſome token of thank<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſſe; ſith I can no way deſerue or recom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pence the leaſt part of your goodnes, I am bold to preſent vnto your honour theſe firſt
<pb facs="tcp:4510:3"/> fruites of my labours, which is the tranſla<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tion of this little treatie; and therefore hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly do pray you it may paſſe vnder your pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tection: the authour wherof, was wel known to ſome godly learned yet liuing amongeſt vs, to be a godly, zealous, and learned prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cher in Fraunce, and many wayes a man of rare giftes. The matter is a chriſtian counſell and direction, how the profeſſours of the Goſpel ſhould behaue and keepe theſelues from being ſtained, or defiled with the ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perſtitions of Poperye, bee they neuer ſo conuerſant amongeſt ſuche as profeſſe the ſame: So that I cannot doubte, but that this little treatyſe wyll haue good ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptance with all the Godlye, and well diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed, both in reſpecte of the Authour, and the matter. But for my ſelfe, who haue taken vppon mee to bee the tranſlatour<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> I maye iuſtlye doubte it can hardelye de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerue allowance, both becauſe my ſkyll is ſhorte to tranſlate with iudegement, and my ſtyle too baſe to haue the handling of ſo good a woorke: yet beeing embol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dened by the allowance of ſome, that haue already ſeene it, and hoping to bee fauoura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blye iudged of by all, that hereafter ſhal per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uſe
<pb facs="tcp:4510:3"/> it, and truſting of your honours well accepting of this my labour, bee it ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer ſo ſimplye perfourmed; I doubte not to put it to the printe, and preſume to dedicate the ſame to your Ladiſhippe. Accept it (good Madam) in liewe of a bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter preſente: And licence mee, in this preface (onely purpoſed to your ſelfe) to ſpeake ſomewhat in a geueralitie to o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers. I finde by experience that Sathans ſhiftes encreaſe dayly, eyther to make vs flatte enemies to religion, or colde friends: for euen amongeſt thoſe, whiche bragge greatly of the Goſpel, and will defie him, that ſhall call him Papiſt, and will ioyne with Gods people in hearing of the worde, and receiuing the Sacramentes, euen a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongeſt theſe there bee ſome, (I ſaye) which are ſo farre ſhorte from true fee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling of religion, that they reſerue to them ſelues a religion for all companies, and can eaſily make ſhift to liue in all ages: and theſe men woulde fayne perſwade them ſelues, that there is ſuch a conueniencie betweene religion and ſuperſtition, betweene the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell and Popery, that they may holde both: they woulde fayne make themſelues to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeue, that the diſſent betweene papiſtes and
<pb facs="tcp:4510:4"/> vs, which doe profeſſe the Goſpel of Chriſt, is only about certaine ceremonies, the vanity of which opinion, is ſo largely confuted by ſundry well learned: that I neede not to ſtand therevpon. But to you, whome the Lord hath ſeaſoned by a better ſpirit, then to profeſſe for faſhions ſake, let me ſpeake bold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly without offence. If you haue well weigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed and conſidered what thraldome your ſelues, or your brethren were in, when Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſtes did beare ſtroke: and had the guiding of this common wealth at their will; you cannot but tell your ſelues how little fauour the zealous profeſſour found, whoſe ſhare it was to receiue al ſharpnes and ſeueritie, that could be deuiſed: and then how can you for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>get to be thankfull vnto God for this our preſent tranquilitie, and peaceable profeſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of his Goſpell, and for our Soueraigne Ladie Queene Elizabeth, his eſpeciall and principall inſtrument thereof: by whom as the chief meanes, we haue been deliuered fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſuperſtition &amp; Popery, &amp; haue been brought to taſt how ſweete the Lord Ieſus is, in the voyce of his goſpel, a bleſſing vnſpeakeable, and ſuch as fewe of our neighbours haue attained vnto in like meaſure, for what na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion can be named, that euer ſo long toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb facs="tcp:4510:4"/> enioyed ſuch quietneſſe as Englande? which ſheweth Gods bleſſing to haue fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed vs moſt gratiouſly in our gouern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment: and what country or nation in the world can be ſhewed to haue the doctrine of the Goſpell, taught generally and by autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie, with more ſoundnes and ſinceritie, then in England: which argueth the great mercy, and fauour of God towords vs, in dayly tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching his prophets to ſpeake, that his truth may ſound in the eares of al that wil willing<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly heare it. But haue we this by deſert: or can we chalenge it before other nations: no, no: but if we learne not to vſe our peace whileſt we haue it, and to take profite by this doct<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rine of ſaluation whileſt we enioy it, &amp; ſhew our ſelues dayly and hourely thankefull for the ſame, our peace ſhall bee taken from vs when we leaſt looke for it; and this Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell will bee giuen vnto a nation that ſhall bring foorth the fruites thereof. Let vs ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore looke about vs in time, leſt we learne to late. Our well ſetled peace in theſe dayes of our godly Prince Edward the ſixt, with the ioyfull libertie of profeſſing Chriſte his Goſpel, which vnder him, we then enioyed, adding hereunto the ſodayne and lamenta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble alteration, which ſucceeded his happye
<pb facs="tcp:4510:5"/> gouernment by his vnlooked for cutting of; might ſufficiently warne vs. We can haue no colour to chalenge this our peace and prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching of the Goſpell in anye certayntie, which both wee enioye onely by the mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cifull goodnes of our good God, who in his fauour and loue hath allotted both vnto vs for our good, if with thankefulneſſe wee receiue them; and can learne to vſe them, to our profite: If otherwiſe wee abuſe them, he can and will in his diſpleaſure for our ſinnes take them from vs, turning peace in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to warre, and the light of his Goſpell into the darkenes of ſuperſtition and poperye. If we will but enter into conſideration with our ſelues, and weigh the ſtate of our neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boures and bretheren in Flaunders, and Fraunce; whome the Lorde, hath long kept vnder the croſſe of affliction and perfe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cution, and withall indifferently compare our offences with theirs; wee ſhall ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſily ſee the zeale of England and to religion farre colder, the obedience to the Goſpel farre ſhorter, al ſinn generally much more aboun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ading. Why then ſhould we looke for the con<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tinuance of theſe bleſſinges without ame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t. If we wil enter into our owne conſcien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces &amp; truly examine our ſelues, whether wee
<pb facs="tcp:4510:5"/> haue beene rightly pinched and grieued at the miſery of our brother Ioſeph: whether wee haue ſighed and mourned before the Lord for Iſraels calamitie: we ſhal finde that ſelfe loue hath borne ſo great a ſwaye in euery of vs all; that we haue been little, or nothing touched with the churches miſerie. Howe then can we looke to eſcape the iuſt iudgement of God, for ſo horrible faultes &amp; defectes: Laſtly, if wee conſider through<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lye, howe mercifullye the Lorde hath dealte with vs in this time of our peace: wherein the Goſpel of our God hath had his free paſſage, and the preaching thereof in many pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces (by Gods mercies) beene moſt plen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifully perfourmed, and weyghe with al, how thankefully we haue receiued the ſame, and what profite wee haue reaped therby: we ſhall the moſt of vs (I feare me) finde our ſelues ſo farre ſhort in eyther, that rather we may feele in our ſelues iuſt cauſe to accuſe our ſelues, for neglecting, contemning, and miſuſing the graces of God, offered vnto vs in this his holy Goſpell. For that we haue neither learned diligently, nor beleeued ſoundly, nor embraced thankfully, nor wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhipped religiouſly, nor confeſſed freely and conſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tly, nor obeyed ſincerely, nor adua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ced
<pb facs="tcp:4510:6"/> zealouſly the will and truth of our God, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uealed vnto vs in the preaching of the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell. But as I accuſe not all, ſo as an aduiſe to all, I ſay with the Apoſtle. <hi>Let him that think<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth he doth stand, take heede he fall not.</hi> And becauſe we haue no inheritance, or ſuch aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurance of this our peace, but that it is to be turned into warre and perſecution, when the Lord our God thinketh good: let vs not fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowe the beaſtly rule of the pampered E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>picures, who ſay to themſelues, <hi>Ede, bibe, lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de, poſt mortem nulla voluptas.</hi> But let vs hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken vnto the wholeſome counſel of the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle Peter. Let vs hence forward learne to liue, as much time as remaineth in the fleſhe, not <note place="margin">1. Pet. 4.</note> after the luſts of men, but after the will of God. For it is ſufficient. &amp;c. For ſurely in fo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing the lewde fancies of fleſhe and blood, we doe tread the path to death, and walke the readie way to deſtruction. But if we ſtriue to mortifye the luſts, and deedes of the fleſhe, we are led by a right line, dyrect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing vs to the true life: that neuer ſhall haue end. Therefore whileſt we enioy the benefite of this our peace, let vs apply our ſelues to the practiſing of that in ſhew we profeſſe, and let vs labour to grow in knowledge, that we may be able to diſcerne the ſpirits and to
<pb facs="tcp:4510:6"/> giue a reaſon of our faith with iudgement &amp; vnderſtanding: So ſhall our peace be greatly profitable vnto vs, and we therby better pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared to abide with patience, what the Lord by perſecution ſhall lay vpon vs. It was not allowed for a good Plea, that the Scribes and phariſees ſhould chalenge themſelues to be the children of Abraham: for that (as our Sauiour Chriſt chargeth them) they did not the workes of their father Abraham, but of their father the Diuell. No more can it be accepted at our hands to chalenge the title of chriſtianitie, to ſay wee profeſſe Chriſt his Goſpell, vnleſſe we bring foorth fruites an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwerable to ſo high a calling. For as Chry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoſtome ſayth. <hi>Non Christi nomen ſolum chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtianum facit, ſed Chriſti veritas, quia in no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine Chriſti multi ambulant in veritate au, tem eius pauci.</hi> And there is no man truely tearmed a chriſtian, but he that ſtriueth to go as neare to Chriſt in his life &amp; conuerſati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, as he ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. Our wel ſelted peace, muſt needs auayle vs much, if we vſe it, and our ſelues in it to the glorifying of our God: for to this end only is our peace preſerued to vs. But if in this time of our peace, we will liue delici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly, walke wantonly, ſleepe in ſinne, and wallow in all manner of ſenſualitie, we ſhall
<pb facs="tcp:4510:7"/> ſurely become falſe prophets to our ſelues, &amp; whileſt we perſwade our ſelues of a pleaſ at peace, beholde preſent deſtruction. The Iſra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>elites groned long vnder the burden of cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ell Pharaoh, who ſeeing them multiplye and encreaſe dayly in number of perſons, and wealth of ſubſtance, he endeuoured and put in practiſe, both by tiranny and cruel ſla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verye to oppreſſe them. But the Lord loking mercifully vpon his people, deliuered them out of the tyrantes handes, and plagued their enemies in moſt ſundry &amp; ſtrange ſorts, and in the end moſt miraculouſly made one ſelf ſa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>e place a paſſage for the deliuery of his children, &amp; pitte of deſtruction to their ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies purſuing them. Yet ſee the ingratitude of mans heart, they were no ſooner deliue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, but they immediately forget ſo great a benefite, and fell to murmuring, grudg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and repining againſt their GOD, who ſo gratiouſly had wrought their deliuerance. I will not apply this, but leaue euery man to his owne conſcience to conſider in himſelfe, whether he hath beene ſufficiently thanke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, for our mercifull and miraculous de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liuerance out of that popiſhe perſecution, practiſed againſt Gods people, in the time of
<pb facs="tcp:4510:7"/> Queene Marye. Or rather, whether that (Gods great bleſſing and benefite therein beeing forgotten) wee haue not throughe ambition, conetouſnes, or carnall ſecuritie, beene ſo drowned in worldly cares, that we haue murmured, grudged, and repined a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt GOD and his miniſters, as the Iſrae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lites did: which being true (as it can hardly be denied) we muſt looke to be trayned vp with the Iſraelites in a newe ſchoole. For when proſperitie and peace could not make them to knowe him, in yeelding due reue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence &amp; obedie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce to him, He viſited the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> with ſharpe roddes and plagues, that by his correction hee might drawe them to ſeeke to him for remedie againſt his ſcourges, and earneſtly to repent them for their rebellion and wickednes agaynſt him. And this did the Lorde of loue to his choſen children, that they might not ſtyll wallow with wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked worldlinges in all licentiouſnes of euill. There be ſome of that vayne and wicked o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinion, who when they cannot couple the Goſpell of Chriſte, and Poperye togea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in the couples of their conceite, as they would do, then they fal to another bare &amp; bad ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ift, perſwading themſelues that they
<pb facs="tcp:4510:8"/> may worſhip God according to the maner of the countries, that they are in, and yet be good Goſpellers ſtill, not remembring that confeſſion of Chriſt, and outward acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledgement of his truth (a ſpeciall part of his worſhip &amp; our ſeruice du to him) is required of vs. For they are the wordes of our Sauiour Chriſt, that we muſt confeſſe him before me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: And who knoweth not, that men cannot ſee into our hearts, therefore with our mouthes we muſt confeſſe him. Notable alſo is that, which the ſpirit of God ſetteth downe by Paule to the Corinthians. Our bodies (ſayth <note place="margin">1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 6.</note> he) are the temples of the holy Ghoſt, and wee are not our owne, for wee are dearelye bought, therefore wee muſt glorifie God in our bodies, &amp; in our ſpirits, for they are gods. Wherby it appeareth, that the Lorde hath ſuch and intereſt &amp; right in vs, &amp; ouer vs; that no half ſeruice ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> pleſe him, but he muſt haue vs whole, and he will be wholy ſerued by vs. Therefore they, that in any reſpect refuſe to confeſſe Chriſt before men, do bewray them ſelues to be eyther faithleſſe, or very fainte in faith: and let them vrge neuer ſo much, that with their inward ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> they ſerue god, &amp; cary a loue to Chriſt his truth, they ſhal finde it is no good plea in diuinitie, neither will
<pb facs="tcp:4510:8"/> it prooue good before God at the generall day of account: when all fleſhe muſt appeare before the iuſt iudge, to giue a reckoning of their ſtewardeſhip. As for thoſe to whom the name of God ſeemeth ſtrange, and are loth to heare of any religion, they are not vnlike to Epicures, of whom it is written: that when he ſaw great contentions amongeſt the phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loſophers touching God, he did take (as hee thought) a ſhorter way, &amp; flatly denied God. Of which kind of men I wiſhe withall my heart, there were not ouer many amo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>geſt vs. It is a dangerous thing, when men become deriders and mockers of the worde, and wil ſcoffe and taunt at ſuch as in reuerent re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard therof, ſeeke to walke according to the preſcript rule, ſet downe by the ſame: for fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> them, by little and little, all ſence and taſt of truth is taken, and they goe on in degrees of vngodlines ſo farre, vntill they ſhewe them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues to be ſuch, as doe hate the truth, and then are they giuen ouer to fulfyll their luſts, making their bellye their GOD, beſtowing their whole life in their owne fylthie &amp; fleſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly pleaſure: for they liue to ſerue no other God indeede, and ſo at length there is with the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> no truth, no religion, no God, but they make a mocke of all religion &amp; truth, and are
<pb facs="tcp:4510:9"/> giuen vp to belieue lyes, and to folowe vanities, and nothing elſe. And thus in fine they beco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>e ſo bold, that they deny God, yea they be ſo cu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ning in the diuels crafe, that they do reaſon againſt God, and openly pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe that Chriſt his truth is but a fable, as this day giueth feareful examples of too ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny: The Lord our God refourm the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, and ſhew them the light of hys countenance, and bee mercifull vnto them. And ſo with griefe to thinke that there ſhould be any ſuch, I leaue them. As for you, who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the Lord hath ſo ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoned by his ſpirit, that you haue learned to bee a law to your ſelues, &amp; do endeuourithat one and the ſelfe ſame woorde, might both teach and rule you, although they giue you bynames for ſo doing: be not difmayed, but hold on your courſe, &amp; be it ſo farre fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> you, to thinke your ſelues pure, &amp; learne to haue ſuch a liuely ſenſe, and feeling of this feſtering fore of ſinne, eating vs to eternal deſtruction, if our Phiſition Chriſt, put not to his helpe to heale the ſame by the blood of his paſſion, as that you acknowledge with the Prophet, all your righteouſnes to be like a ſtayned cloth, and to this end labour in your ſelues, &amp; per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwade it in others to go on ſtill, and to be cli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming vp from ſtep to ſtep, towards the mark
<pb facs="tcp:4510:9"/> of perfectio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſet before vs: not thinking it ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficient to begin well, and there to ſtay, nor to goe and grow forward for a time, and the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to ſtand ſtill, but we muſt know that perſeuera<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce hath the promiſe, for he that perſeuereth to the end, he ſhalbe ſaued. This then being the ſetled perſwaſion of all that truely feare the Lord, let not their courſe be hindered, ney<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in their courſe let them be diſcouraged, but carrying in the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues the teſtimony of a good conſcience, that they haue in the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſelues a deſire to encreaſe daily from fayth to faith, from knowledge to knowledge, from godli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe to godlineſſe, vntill they become per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect men in Chriſt Ieſus: let them knowe it is their glory to beare reproch for good dea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling. See that none of you (ſaith the Apoſtle) ſuffer as a murtherer, as a theefe, as an euill doer, or as a buſie bodie in other mens mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, but if anye man ſuffer as a Chriſtian &amp;c. <note place="margin">1. Pet. 4.</note> This is the portion of Gods people, to ſuffer for wel doing; and of this we ought not to be aſhamed, but for this we muſt glorifie God: neither is this the vttermoſt of our triall, to be euil ſpoken of, but we are like to taſte the ſmart of a more ſharpe ſchoole: Our ſinnes prouoke it, Gods iuſtice doth threaten it, and
<pb facs="tcp:4510:10"/> I ſee not how we ſhould auoyd it. Let vs learn therefore to be wel prouided againſt the day of tryal. And ſurely if we profeſſe, as we ſeem, or carry that ſincere zeale, as we ought, wee haue caſt our reckoning, we know the pryce, and therefore will endeuour to prouide for paiment. <hi>Crux comes Euangely:</hi> is an old rule, and he is a very delicate, or rather faintehear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted ſouldiour, that loketh to ouer come with out fighting: or to winne victory with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out contending: and how can he fight, that is vnprepared to the battell? or contend for victory, that is vnprouided? And to be armed at all poyntes, This leſſon well learned, wyll teach vs that, <hi>Tota vita Chriſtiani hominss, ſi ſecundum Euangelium uiuat, eſt crux at<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyrium.</hi> Let not your heartes be troubled therefore, neither feare, and let your patient mynds be knowen vnto all men, for the Lord is at hand. It is notably ſaid of a learned Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, that tribulation and trouble is to a iuſt man, as the file to the yro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, the fornace to the gold, the bridle to the horſe, and the whippe to the Aſſe. The fyle, as it is commonly ſeene, maketh yron the brighter, the fyery fornace maketh gold the more glorious, the bridle withholdeth the headdy horſe, that hee goe not whither him liſteth, the whippe keepeth
<pb facs="tcp:4510:10"/> the dul Aſſe in ſuch awe, that he dare not but goe on. And this doth affliction to euery true Chriſtian. Let vs not be diſmayed therefore, though our peace be taken from vs, and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecution come in place: For to vs that haue a ſure teſtimonie ſealed vp in our conſciences, that we are Gods children, it ſhall turne to great good, beyng ſure that our heauenly fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther wil lay no more vpon vs, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he wil make vs well able to beare. We ſee by experience, that where the Prince or chiefe Magiſtrate fauoureth the profeſſion of the Goſpel, the moſt part wilbe Goſpellers. But like experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence hath taught vs, when times of tryall haue come vpon them, what time ſeruers ſome haue ſhewed themſelues. But to ſuche, our god co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>meth not as a correcting father, but as a deſtroying iudge. For obedience to the Lorde God, and the profeſſion of his truth, is not tyed to the pleaſure of Princes. He that confeſſeth me before men, I will confeſſe him before my father in heauen. But he that denyeth me. &amp;c. And we muſt learne to ſay with the Apoſtle Paule. If I ſeeke to pleaſe men, I am not the ſeruant of Chriſt. It is an olde ſaying and a true. All is not Gold that gliſtereth, but the fiery fornace wil ſoon try it. Euery piece of yron that wee ſee, is not
<pb facs="tcp:4510:11"/> perfect and ſound yron, for ſometimes it is eaten through with the canker; and this, when the file commeth vpon it, is eaſily knowne. Wheate and chaffe lye mingled to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether in one barne, til a gale of wind come, and blowe them in ſunder, and then they ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peare both plainely what they are: let vs ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quaint our ſelues with our good GOD by continuall and heartie prayer, that by his goodnes wee may bee prepared againſt the day of his viſitation, to abide what in mercy he ſhall think good to lay vpon vs. The feare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulnes of fleſhe and blood is ſuch, and the delight therof in worldly proſperity ſo great, that aduerſitie is not eaſily borne. Impriſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment is accounted painefull, but it is more painefull to enioy libertie vpon euill condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions. The priſons are thought lothſome &amp; vnſauery, but yet not more lothſome, then the ſweeteſt houſes, where the feare of God is wanting. It is grieuous to man to be ſoli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tary and alone, yet better is it to be ſo, then in companie with the wicked. It toucheth vs very neare to looſe liuing and goodes, but it ſhal be found to touch nearer to looſe the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uour and grace of God. We vſe it as a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon ſpeech, that life is ſweete, but moſt ſweete and pleaſant is it to looſe this life, full
<pb facs="tcp:4510:11"/> of mortall miſeries, to finde and enioye the life full of eternall ioyes. We are loth to leaue our friendes, wife, and children, but we muſt beware, that in abiding with them wee ſtay not in the diſpleaſure of our God. Theſe tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>als muſt needes come vpon vs, and whoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>euer liueth to it, is like to taſt of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. But be of good cheare, Whom the Lord loueth, hee chaſtiſeth, euen to this ende, that hee might call them to remember their ſinnes, and ſo runne by repentance to him and aſke mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy: and then he might pardon and forgiue them, in reſpect wherof we are not to lame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, but to prayſe the Lorde, not to be diſmaide, but to be co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>forted, that our God wil vouch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſafe to offer vs his croſſe: whereby he ſeeketh to traine vs vp to the place of endleſſe ioye and comfort. It is an aſſurance laide vp vnto vs, that if we ſuffer, we ſhall raigne. If we con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe him before men in earth, hee will con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe vs beefore his father in heauen. If wee bee not aſhamed of his Goſpell heere, he will not be aſhamed of vs at the laſt daye. Remember the words of our ſauiour Chriſt in the. 5. of Mathew. Bleſſed are they that ſuffer perſecution for righteouſnes ſake, for theires is the kyngdome of heauen. Call to
<pb facs="tcp:4510:12"/> mynde that which Paule ſaith in the 8. to the Romaines. The afflictions of this life, are not to be compared to the ioyes of the lyfe pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared for you. Wherefore ſeeing that euen in the croſſe we beholde and ſee the mercie of our God, which is more ſweete, and to be ſet by then any mucke or pelfe of this world, yea much more then is life it ſelfe. Let vs keepe on our courſe, Let vs walke before our God in ſimplicitie of heart, knowing this, that not a heyre of heade can periſh without the wil of our heauenly father, neither can a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny man, or diuel be able to atte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pt any thing, much leſſe to do any thing to vs, without the ſufferance of the Almightie: And when leaue is graunted, they ſhall goe no further then he will. Wherefore caſting all our care vppon the Lord, who careth ſufficiently for vs: Let vs lay aſide all feare, and onely ſtudie, whileſt we liue heare, to pleaſe him, and to keepe our conſciences cleane from the pollutions of this preſent age, that both our minde and tongue, our life and beliefe may be anſwera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to eche other, and that for euer the word of truth may be a light to lighten our ſteps in the path of true holines. The Lorde in the riches of his mercy impart vnto vs all, ſuch
<pb facs="tcp:4510:12"/> portion of his holy ſpirit, that when the time of our tryall ſhall come, and that the winde of perſecution ſhall blow vpon vs, we may be founde pure golde, made clearer by the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nace, &amp; perfect yron, bryghtened by the fyle, and good Wheate, ſeuered from the light chaffe, and ſo conſtantly continue Chriſt his faythfull ſouldiers, and ſeruantes to our liues end. And thus (Madam) haue I dedicated to your ſelfe particulerly a tranſlated treatiſe, as a pledge of my reuerend loue I beare you: and to others, generally a long and rude Epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle with it. Your ſelfe I truſt will accept my ſimple trauaile therin, &amp; take it in good part: and others, I hope, to whoſe handes this E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſtle and treatiſe ſhall come, will make fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uourable conſtruction thereof, and will beare with all defectes therein, whatſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>euer. My deſire was to warne &amp; encourage, which how weakely ſoeuer it be perfourmed, I truſt it ſhall no whit hinder, but rather fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to ſo neceſſary a meditation, that obtai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, I haue my deſire: beſeeching God to o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen our eyes, that we may ſee our deſerts, &amp; thereby know our perils, and knowing the ſame, may labour to meete the Lord by re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance, before he come: whether it bee for a time to ſcourge vs in iuſtice, or to performe
<pb facs="tcp:4510:13"/> the laſt time of his comming in iudgement, to euery one, the portion allotted vnto him for his hire, from the beginning: which time of his comming, the Lorde haſten to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forme and fulfill for his electes ſake.</p>
            <closer>Amen.</closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:4510:13"/>
            <head>¶ <hi>Grace, mercie, and peace,</hi> from God our Father, through our Lorde Ieſus Chriſt.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> Was very glad (deere bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren) when I vnderſtood how God of his goodnes &amp; mercie, had viſited you to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> grace of the holy Goſpell, and to the knowledge of his truth: and thereby to the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion of his ſonne Ieſus Chriſt, who is the treaſure of all ages, for this is a treaſure con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teyning immortall riches, wherein lyeth all our bleſſednes and felicitie: this is an ineſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mable benefite, and the greateſt wée coulde re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue of God. Wherefore we haue good cauſe to giue him thankes for the ſame continually, to the intent, that by our ingratitude, wee may not prouoke him to anger againſt vs, nor ſtirre him vp, or moue him to take from vs the talent which he hath giuen vs: for we may well ſay of our ſelues, that which Dauid ſaid of himſelfe, and of all the people of God. The Lorde hath not thus done to all nations, neither hath hee manifeſted to them his iudgements. When a king taketh ſome one into his ſeruice, and gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth
<pb facs="tcp:4510:14"/> him ſome honorable office in his Court, we thinke it a greate honour vnto him which is called to ſuch a promotion, and eſteeme him greately beholding and bounde to the King. Let vs then thinke what cauſe we haue to glorifie and magnifie GOD our fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, ſeeyng that wee ſee hee is come to e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lect and chooſe vs from amongeſt all other, not onelye to be his ſeruantes, but alſo to bee his children, and to bee kinges and heyres of his kingdome: and that he leaueth a greate number of others that bee wyſer, richer, and that beare a greater ſhewe then wee, to put the treaſures of his grace into ſo poore veſſels of earth as we be; ſo vyle, ſo baſe, ſo weake, ſo frayle and brittle.</p>
            <p>And therefore wee ought greatly to feare <note place="margin">Sect.</note> to abuſe this greate goodnes of GOD tow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ardes vs, and the giftes which wee haue recea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued of him: we muſt take good heede wee hyde them not in the earth, as the ſlouthfull and vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faithfull ſeruant did hide his talent, but as the other good and faithfull ſeruauntes did, we muſt put them to ſome vſe, to the intent they maye bring foorth fruite to their Mai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter and Lorde, who to this ende hath pu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> them into our handes: for why doth GOD call vs into his ſeruice, but to ſerue him:
<pb facs="tcp:4510:14"/> why doth GOD communicate his graces vnto vs, but that wee ſhoulde employe them to his honour and glorie, and to the edifiyng of his Churche: howe can wee bee Gods ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uantes and remayne idle in his houſe and doe nothing: but (which is worſe) how will he ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer vs there, if in ſteede of ſeruing Chriſt Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus; we ſerue Antichriſt and the Deuill his ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſaries: Let vs therefore remember y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> which the Lorde ſayth: To him that hath, it ſhalbee giuen, and to him that hath nothing, it ſhalbe taken from him euen that he hath.</p>
            <p>Wee ſee this by experience before our eyes euerye day to come to paſſe: wee ſee <note place="margin">Sect.</note> howe GOD encreaſeth his graces towards them which vſe them as they ought, and how on the contrary he depriueth them thereof which abuſe them: and howe hee giueth them vp into a reprobate ſenſe, for when they knewe GOD, they glorified him not as God, but gaue the honour which appertey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth to him onelie, to creatures and Idols. Wherefore we ought not to maruell if we ſee many to who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> God hath giue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſome knowledge of truth, which become (godles) &amp; mockers of holy ſcriptures, &amp; to become as dogges to eate that which they once vomited, and as ſwyne to wallowe themſelues in the myre and filthe,
<pb facs="tcp:4510:15"/> out of the which God had drawen them, wee cannot doubt, but ſuch a curſe is the moſt horri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble &amp; moſt fearefull iudgement of God, which can come to man, it is the iudgement which he is woont to execute vpon the ingratefull, and contemners of his word, and blaſphemers of his graces: therefore let vs take heede that we neither dally of him nor with him: let vs hearken how the Apoſtle warneth vs, let vs not abuſe our ſelues, for God can neither be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luded nor mocked.</p>
            <p>And therefore let vs learne to walke with <note place="margin">Sect.</note> him in all feare, honour, and reuerence, let vs make our profite of his ſeuere iudgement, whiche hee ſetteth before our eyes as in a glaſſe, when hee puniſheth ſo ſharply thoſe which after they had known him, haue forſake<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> him, and deſpiſed his worde: let vs beware we eſteeme not lightly anye thing that hee hath commaunded or forbidden, but let vs feare to offende him in anye thing whatſoeuer, ey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in omitting that which hee hath comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded vs to doe, or in doyng that which he hath forbidden.</p>
            <p>Let vs looke more to the authoritie of the <note place="margin">Sect.</note> Lawe maker, and to his will, then to the naked lawe: and let vs iudge thereof according to his will and not according to our owne,
<pb facs="tcp:4510:15"/> let vs conſider with our ſelues, that we cannot tranſgreſſe the left commandement that euer he gaue without deſpiſing his maieſtie and au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoritie: For if we regard not his commaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dements, we declare manifeſtly thereby, that wee feare him not, but that we dally with him, as though wee helde him in our ſleeue to doe with him as pleaſeth vs: or els we giue to vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d, that we wil correct him, as not well ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiſed, and as though he had fayled eyther in co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maunding, or forbidding things vnworthy to be co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maunded or forbidden. Ought this arro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ga<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cy &amp; preſumptio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, &amp; deſpiſing of god his autho<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rity to be eſteemed a ſmal fault: Is it not grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter then high treaſon: ſeeing that the Maieſty and authority of God paſſeth all authoritie and excellencie of man? What leſſe puniſhment then, can he deſerue then death and eternal da<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation, if God wil condemne him according to the rigour of his iudgement:</p>
            <p>And therefore my brethren, wee muſt take <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Sect.</hi> Sedu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing of himſelfe.</note> good heede, that wee deceaue not our ſelues, or that we ſuffer not our ſelues to bee eaſilye ſeduced by others, which may bee among vs, for many doe boaſt of the knowledge of God, which notwithſtanding make no great conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence to doe contrary to his will in all things, which are of no ſmall importance, which not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ding
<pb facs="tcp:4510:16"/> ſeeme to them very ſmal, becauſe they perſwade themſelues ſo, and that they iudge thereof according to their owne affectio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. But if they did iudge of them, according to the iudgeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſpirit of God, they ſhould know y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> they are very vnpleaſant &amp; deteſtable before God, &amp; of that nature, that there is nothing that he doth more abhorre &amp; deteſt, nor that hee hath puniſhed more grieuouſly at al times: It is not a ſmall matter to prouoke God to anger, and we cannot more prouoke him, then by Idola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trie and ſuperſtition, which is the fountaine of all other euils, and a ſinne which doth eſtrange and draw vs wholly from God.</p>
            <p>Let vs not abuſe our ſelues, for it may ſeeme to vs that the thinges which wee doe <note place="margin">Sect.</note> to keepe vs in league with the children of this worlde, are not of great importance. Let vs beware that Sathan drawe vs not from obey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the commandement of GOD by the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceaueablenes of our fleſhe, as he withdrew A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam by the meanes of Eue, after that by his <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Gen.</hi> 3.</note> lye ſhe was ſeduced, he thought with himſelfe it was no greate faulte, to eate of the fruite of a Tree, but it was very great, ſith GOD had forbidden it, as experience taught it af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terwarde: for by this tranſgreſſion all the ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nage of man was deſtroyed and all creatures
<pb facs="tcp:4510:16"/> were made ſubiect to Curſe.</p>
            <p>Let vs neuer ſuffer therfore y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> word of God <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Sect.</hi> To hold the word faſt.</note> to bee ſnatched out of our handes whatſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer reaſon, or whatſoeuer colour or cloke fleſhe can alleadge vnto vs: let vs bee as warye as wee woulde bee to fall into the fire, to drawe backe from this worde, and to abandon it, one only ſteppe. For wee neede not goe farre aſide to miſſe the waye, to ſet vs altogether out of the way, and when one is once fallen out of the way, the further hee goeth on, the further hee wandreth and mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiplyeth errour vppon errour: ſo that after it is verye harde for him to finde his right waye, and to come thither, whether hee purpoſed. Wherefore to auoyde the falling into the bottome of the depth of ſinne, let vs gette vs awaye out of hand from the banks, leaſt we plunge our ſelues in deeper then wee thinke for, and that there come not ſome waue which ſodenly wil ſet vpon vs, and in wray and plunge vs in ſuch ſort among the waues, that we can neuer get out, but remayne there all to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether drowned.</p>
            <p>If wee will well flie ſinne, let vs keepe vs as farre from it, as wee can, and take heede <note place="margin">Sect.</note> not onely to touch it, but alſo to come neere it,
<pb facs="tcp:4510:17"/> for it is ſo infectious a plague, and ſo ſtinking and dangerous a poyſon, that although one <note place="margin">The ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner to flie ſinne.</note> keepe himſelfe backe from it ſo farre as is poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible, yet can he not auoyde, but that he ſhalbee infected &amp; corrupted therewith. A man cannot haue ſo ſmall acquaintance therewith, but that <note place="margin">Acquain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance w<hi rend="sup">c</hi> ſinne.</note> immediatly it wilbe turned into ouer great fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miliarity and boldnes, and then into a cuſtome, which cannot be ſhake<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> off: as we ſee it by expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rience in all ſortes of ſinne. And to knowe theſe more playnely, let vs take one exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple which may ſerue vs for all the reſt, and which ſhalbee very agreeable to the matter, wee haue in hande; let vs conſider by what way a harlot commeth to the laſt ſteppe of infamye and abhomination: ſhee ſlippeth not, nor ſlideth awaye like an eale as a common harlot at the firſt day, but firſt ſhee beginneth to wander a little out of the bondes of modeſty, ſhamefaſtnes, and honeſty, which ought to bee in a woman that is vertuous and full of the feare of God: ſhe delighteth to heare &amp; ſpeake diſhoneſt and infamous wordes, and to ſing filthy and wicked ſonges: ſhe taketh pleaſure in daunces, and to bee conuerſant amongſt lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſty youthes, and feedeth her eyes with their ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſture &amp; cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tenances, &amp; her eares to heare their amorous and laſciuious talke: after ſhee hath
<pb facs="tcp:4510:17"/> once abandoned her eyes and eares, ſhee is no longer whole and chaſt. For we cannot thinke that woman truly chaſt, which is not ſo in heart and minde, and in all partes and members of her bodye, they that knowe what honeſtie and chaſtitie is, will iudge hereof in this ſorte, for they cannot call things, but by their name: but they which take pleaſure in ſuch paſtimes, as harlots, and ſuch other worldlings, carnall folkes, and curtizans, which can diſguiſe and change the names of things, wil not cal theſe laſciuious loue trickes wicked wantonnes, but ciuilitie and curteſie, notwithſtanding whatſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>euer name, me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> giue to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> thing, yet ſhal it be al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes, what it is, and ſhall not change the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, for the alteratio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> and change of names: ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing then the eyes &amp; eares are already wonne, the other partes are not very ſure: after theſe follow other dalianees as tickings or toyings, which defile the body yet ſomewhat more and more enflameth to whoredome: when chaſtitie is once violated ſo farre, it will goe hard, if in ſhort ſpace it periſh not altogether, and that whoredome follow not incontinently thervp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, notwithſtanding at the beginning there will bee ſome ſhamefaſtneſſe, which will keepe it ſecret: but after by proceſſe of time and long cuſtome, this ſhamefaſtneſſe will fall by little
<pb facs="tcp:4510:18"/> and little, ſo that the ſecret harlot will become altogether impudent without any ſhame at al, or feare of God or man. As much may we ſay of all other ſinnes: for it is all one reaſon: By little ſteppes a man commeth to the heape and depth of ſinne: But I haue willingly taken the example of whoredome, becauſe it is moſt like vnto idolatrie.</p>
            <p>There is then no leſſe danger, but that as <note place="margin">Sect.</note> much will happen vnto vs, if wee yeelde the leaſt thing in the worlde to idolatry and ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtition: for by the one we come to the other, if for feare of grieuing our fleſhe and to depriue it of the pleaſures it delighteth in, we goe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout to flatter it, and beginne ſomewhat to giue it the bridle, it is in greate hazard that it will take the bitte in the teeth, and that hauing the bridle at wil, it will take a courſe, wherein we can neyther ſtop it nor draw it from thence when we would: If we ſuffer it to goe to daun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſings, to enter into brothell houſes, to keepe companye to daunce and paſſe the time with baudes, whores, and harlots, hardly ſhall it returne chaſt without ſome loſſe of the chaſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie it ought to haue. Then to enter into idoles temples, to bee conuerſant and communicate with Idolaters, and to beholde their iuglings, and to be there aſſiſtant with them, &amp; to daunce
<pb facs="tcp:4510:18"/> the ſame daunce that they doe, what is it elſe, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to enter into the brothel houſes of Satha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> &amp; to be acquainted with Baudes and Harlots: whiche committe fornication with ſtraunge Gods.</p>
            <p>If a man deſire to haue his wife chaſte both in bodie and minde, and cannot loue her if ſhee <note place="margin">Sect.</note> hath giuen awaye her loue and ſetled her heart vpon another, or that ſhee hath yeelded or permitted him (I ſay) not her whole bodye, but onely her mouth to kiſſe her, or her necke, or armes to embrace her: Think we that Ieſus Chriſt deſireth not his ſpouſe to be much more pure both in body and mind: Think, we that he can abide that we ſhould dedicate our heart to any other than to him: Thinke we that he de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lighteth, that we ſhould make this body a me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of an harlot, a temple of Idoles, and of the Diuell, and a brothell houſe of Sathan, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of Ieſus is the head, and which he hath conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crated &amp; ſanctified as a ſoueraigne biſhop, to be the temple of God and dwelling houſe of the holy Ghoſt: Thinke we that he can abide that we ſhould come euery day in his ſight, and hu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble our ſelues before the ſtrumpet of Babylon and do reuerence to Baal, &amp; kiſſe ſtra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge gods, &amp; pollute al y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>bers of our body through ſuch fornicatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s &amp; adulteries: We may perceiue it
<pb facs="tcp:4510:19"/> by that which is written in the Lawe. Thou ſhalt haue none other Gods before me, nor in my preſence. Thou ſhalt doe no homage nor reuerence to Images. He doth not forbid vs onely to ſettle our heartes thereon, But that wee ſhould not bowe downe or make any ſigne of honour or reuerence to them at al: The huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bande, who that after hee hath reconciled his wife to him, ſhould ſee her frequent the houſe of the adulterer that ſeduced her, and ſee her eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry day in his armes kiſſing her, imbracing her, and dallying with her, what account could bee make of her, but that ſhe is a falſe, impudent, and deſperate ſtrumpet: And if ſhee were an honeſt woman ſhould ſhe not abhorre, euen to ſee him or his houſe, or to heare talke of him: Ought ſhe not to feare (if ſhe were not too im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pudent or ouer much ingratefull) to caſt her eyes towards him, whether it were in preſence or abſence of her huſband: Ought ſhee not to feare to prouoke him againſt her, and to giue occaſion as well to him as to all others, to haue ſome euill opinion and ſuſpition of her, which might redound to the diſhoneſting, and defa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming as well of her as of her huſband.</p>
            <p>Ought we not to content our ſelues to haue <note place="margin">Sect.</note> liued ſo long &amp; beue conuerſant in the brothel houſe of Sathan, and to haue continued in our
<pb facs="tcp:4510:19"/> fornications and adulteries; but that wee muſt returne thither againe euery day and euery houre, as though of ſet purpoſe wee had determined to prouoke y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Lord to ielouſie &amp; to anger, making our members ſeruantes to all filthineſſe, vncleanneſſe, idolatrie and ſuperſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion: how is it poſſible that we ſhould acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> great grace and mercie, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> God hath be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtowed on vs, in withdrawing vs out of this ſincke ful of blaſphemies and abhominations, in ſteede of reiecting vs and caſting vs of, as an Adultereſſe which hath violated and broke<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> her fayth to her huſband, and that we make ſo light account to be conuerſant alwayes with our olde companions, and to ſerue them, with ſo great diſhonour to our true Spouſe Ieſus Chriſt.</p>
            <p>Wherefore I greatly maruaile that ſuche kinde of ſpirits are to be found amongeſt thoſe <note place="margin">Sect.</note> which will haue the names to follow the goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell, and to be counted of the number of Diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples of Chriſt Ieſus, which dare yet mainteine that the faithfull and thoſe to whome God hath reuealed the truth of his Goſpel may commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicate with idolaters and ſuperſtitious per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, in their idolatries, and ſuperſtitions, and be partaker, of the tables of Diuels, whervnto we cannot approch without ouerthrowing the
<pb facs="tcp:4510:20"/> table of Chriſt Ieſus: I tremble when I heart that ſuch ſpeeches paſſe, from the mouthes of thoſe which boaſt themſelues of the Goſpell, and ſo much the more, for that ſo boldlie, they dare giue that councell to others: for their o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinions are ſo farre contrarie to truth, and ſo ſtrange to any good Chriſtian heart, that it were better ſuch men had neuer heard ſpeake of Chriſt Ieſus nor his religion.</p>
            <p>I knowe not what Goſpel or Scripture <note place="margin">Sect.</note> they haue ſtudied, nor howe they dare ſo open<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly gainſay the ſpirit of God: which pronoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceth ſo plainely that there is no agreement <note place="margin">2. 10. 6. <hi>Ephe.</hi> 6.</note> with light and darknes, with Chriſt and belial, with the temple of God and the temple of I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doles. To what end exhorteth he the faythfull <note place="margin">There is no agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene Chriſt &amp; Beliall.</note> by his holy Apoſtle, not to cary &amp; draw y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> yoke among Infidels, and not to communicate any kinde of way with the vnfruitfull woorkes of darkeneſſe: but commandeth rather to reproue and condemne them. I know wel from what ſchoole, this diuinitie proceedeth, not from the ſchoole of the ſpirit of God: from the ſchoole of the fleſhe which liketh not well to come out of Egypt, and to renou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce the pleaſures and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lightes thereof: therefore it ſeeketh coulor in the holy ſcriptures to cloake and couer her in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmitie, becauſe it dare not openly gaineſaye
<pb facs="tcp:4510:20"/> the word of God, whereby it is ouercome.</p>
            <p>I haue heard and examined ſome reaſons <note place="margin">Sect.</note> and arguments, whereby thoſe (whome ſuche doctrine pleaſeth) goe about to confirme and approue it: but they are too friuolous &amp; weake, and ſufficiently ouerthrowe themſelues, if one behold them narrowly. I know well that ſuch <note place="margin">Delicate Chriſtia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s.</note> reaſons are forged in ſome mens braine, flat contrary to Moſes: for they delight too muche in Pharaos court, which it grieueth them muche to forſake, to bee conuerſant in the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſert with the people of God: They haue not yet learned to preferre with Moſes the appro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bries, pouerties, and miſeries, nor the nayles and thornes of Ieſus Chriſt, before the tempo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Iewels, treaſures and delightes of Egypt; they are conſtrained by vertue of the trueth, to acknowledge that the ſuperſtition and ido<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latrie wherein they haue liued, is damnable: wherefore they are forced and conſtrained in conſcience to conde<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ne it, which willingly they do, when they may without danger: but becauſe they will ſuffer nothing for trueth, &amp; yet they dare not condemne it nor reiect it, but will bee counted amongeſt the faithful for good men, &amp; for fauourers and defendours therof, &amp; not for blaſphemers and perſecutors: they trauaile as much as they may to finde ſome cloke in the woorde of GOD, to couer and hide their
<pb facs="tcp:4510:21"/> to great infirmitie of their fayth, and the forni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cations which the fleſhe committeth euery day with ſtrange Gods.</p>
            <p>Such poore blinde ſoules ſhould doe much <note place="margin">Sect.</note> better to acknowledge and confeſſe their mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerie and incredulity, deſiring pardon and mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie of God whom they offend, then to defende and flatter them ſelues in it: they ought to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues, to offe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d God many other waies, &amp; not to abuſe in ſuch ſort y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> holy ſcriptures, nor blaſpheme the holy Ghoſt, in corrupting them, and wreſting them to make them ſerue their own affection, &amp; to builde therby, entertain &amp; e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtabliſh idolatrie and iniquitie: which ought by them wholy to be beaten downe and deſtroyed: It is eaſie to be perceiued, that ſuch Chriſtians haue neuer yet truely vnderſtood the grounds, rudiments, and principles of the Chriſtians re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion: for they will be the diſciples of Chriſt Ieſus, without renouncing themſelues, and without carrying their croſſe after him, which is impoſſible. For the maiſter hath <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> the ſcholer is not aboue his maiſter, nor <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uant <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mat.</hi> 10. <hi>Iohn.</hi> 13. <hi>Luk.</hi> 14.</note> aboue his Lord, it ought to ſuffice <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſciples and ſeruants to be as their ma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>er is. And therefore he that will bee my ſcholer, hee muſte renounce him ſelfe, carry his croſſe eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry day vpon his ſhoulders, and followe mee, he
<pb facs="tcp:4510:21"/> that hateth not, (that is as he expoundeth it in another place) he that loueth his father or mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mat.</hi> 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. 16.</note> brethren, ſiſters, or wife, or children, or houſe and poſſeſſions more then me, he is not worthie to be with me, nor to bee my diſciple. Wherfore it were much better for theſe Doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tours to learne, then to teach, they ought ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to pray to God that he would ſtrengthen them to confeſſe and ſanctifie his holy name, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to take ſuch boldnes vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to deny him, &amp; to endeuour to draw others into y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> like errour.</p>
            <p>We ſee by expertence, the fruite that com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth <note place="margin">Sect.</note> out of this pernitious doctrine, and into what pit it draweth them at length, which ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by will paynt themſelues a Chriſt after their owne fantaſie, farre contrary vnto him that ſaid vnto ſuch a Diſciple as they woulde bee. The foxes haue holes, and the birdes of heauen their neſtes: But the Sonne of man hath not <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mat.</hi> 9.</note> whereon to lay his heade. But theſe men will haue caſtles and pallaces, and will liue in the courtes of princes. And becauſe ſuch thinke it too ſharpe to rub and eate the eares of corne with Ieſus Chriſt as his Diſciples did, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire to finde the ta<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>e layd, they make no great conſcience to bow the knee to Baall, and after that once they haue accuſtomed themſelues to that, they take no heede, but that by little and
<pb facs="tcp:4510:22"/> litle, the knowledge of god which they had re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceaued, and that litle meaſure of fayth whiche perhaps they had, beginneth to waxe cold, and altogether to bee extinguiſhed, and after that they fall into ſuch deſpiſing of God and his word, that they are much worſe, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> they which neuer knewe God.</p>
            <p>Wherefore wee muſt take heede, of that <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Sect.</hi> Tranſfi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gurati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>than. 2. <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.</note> ſame ſubtill (Sathan) who can ſo well tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fourme him ſelfe into an angell of light, to make the truth of God to ſerue our affections, and to change it into a lye and blaſphemy: whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Sathan knoweth that there is any feare of God, and any knowledge of truth in vs, and y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> we do any thing reuere<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> holy ſcriptures, he armeth him ſelfe to fight againſt vs by the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mat.</hi> 4.</note> and hee alleadgeth them to vs, as hee did to Chriſt Ieſus when he tempted him. <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Luk.</hi> 4.</note>
            </p>
            <p>This Sathan is very dangerous, who ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth the ſtaffe of the word of God, to beate vs withall, wherewith he ought to beaten: and therewith he giueth vs dangerous woundes. The firſt is, that he mooueth vs to blaſpheme God. The ſecond is, (which is made woorſe) that he maketh vs to beleeue and thinke that it is not wickedly done, but that it is lawful for vs to doe ſo, at the leaſt, it is a ſmall ſinne and amongſt the leſt that we can commit; &amp; which
<pb facs="tcp:4510:22"/> is more, to the entent we ſhould not periſh a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>one in our errours, hee pricketh vs forward, to entiſe others to doe the like. And to the end he may bee more couert and leſſe knowen, to giue a better cloke to theſe reaſons, he layeth ſtraight before vs Naaman the Sirian, or Ni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>codemus, or Saint Paule, which applyeth him ſelfe to all, and who made himſelfe a Iewe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongeſt <note place="margin">1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 9. <hi>Sect.</hi>
               </note> Iewes, &amp; a gentyle amo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gſt gentyles.</p>
            <p>I doubt not but theſe reaſons ſeeme fayre and pleaſant to the fleſhe, and that it loueth ſuch proctors and aduocates which will ſo excuſe &amp; <note place="margin">Proctors and aduo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cates of the fleſhe.</note> iuſtifie it: but it muſt take heede that they vſe her not as aduocates and proctors, thoſe are without conſcience and without the feare of God, and which haue no other God but Golde and ſiluer: and haue no regard, ſo they haue mo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ney: ſuch proctors and aduocates will make the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> beleeue, whoſe cauſe they defend, that their matter is good, although it be the worſt &amp; fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſt that may be: for euery ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> eaſily beleeueth y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> which he deſireth, &amp; that which pleaſeth him, &amp; he hath affectio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vnto: &amp; therfore M. aduocate knowing y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> affection of man abuſeth him to his profit &amp; gaine, &amp; to the hurt of the pore conten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der: for if he would tell him at the firſt, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he had an euil cauſe, hee woulde ſtaye from pleading, if hee were wiſe, and woulde purſue that
<pb facs="tcp:4510:23"/> cauſe no more, but would doe that which were right and reaſon, and ſo the aduocate ſhoulde gain nothing: Or if he were an obſtinate perſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, and affectioned aboue meaſure to his cauſe &amp; againſt his partie, he woulde be vexed and an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grie againſt his aduocate, and woulde iudge him ignorant and ſcant cunning in his arte for telling him trueth: And therfore would goe ſeeke another more to his liking; for it is the nature of man to iudge all thinges according to his affection and for his aduantage. If thou ſpeake to his fanſie thou ſhalt be the learnedſt man in the world: but if thou bee contrarye to his opinion, thou ſhalt be but a beaſt, and haſte loſt immediatly all thy learning: and therefore our fleſh will haue aduocates to defend their cauſe well, and to allowe what ſhee deſireth: &amp; ſeeing it hath ſuch a deſire, ſhee ſhall no more lacke ſuch fellowes as ſhee deſireth, then the ſame proctors which take pleaſure in conten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, ſpending their money, looſing their time, and conſuming their bodies and ſoules in ſtrife and debate.</p>
            <p>But what profit ſhall they haue to caſt a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way <note place="margin">Sect.</note> and deſtroy them ſelues: for the ſentence ſhall not be giuen by the aduocate and proctor, nor according to their deſire, but by the iudge and ſuch as ſhall pleaſe him: and when M. Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uocate
<pb facs="tcp:4510:23"/> ſhall ſee that the cauſe of his Client go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth euill, whome he hath alwayes kept in good hope till the laſt caſt, he will ſhake him of well enough and leaue him in the myre where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in he hath plunged him: for he hath his recko<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, he hath fiſhed in a troubled water, he hath plucked the bird, he hath the feathers &amp; the fat, and careth no more for the cauſe: and therefore let vs take good heede, that we delight not in ſuch defenders and aduocates: for there maye be enough found, which to pleaſe vs and bee in our fauour, and well accounted of; will flatter vs, and tell vs pleaſant thinges: wee prooue it true in many bellies, whiche haue founde ſuche taſt in the Kitchin of Egypt; that they thinke them ſelues vtterly loſt, ſo ſoone as they haue loſt the ſight of the ſmoke. But when we ſhall appeare before the iudgement of God, the diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putation ſhal not there be decided, nor the cauſe there iudged by their reaſons, nor according to their ſentence, but by the iuſt iudgment of God which is alwayes in truth.</p>
            <p>And therefore let vs count them more deare, <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Sect.</hi> Let vs flee flatterers and Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raſites.</note> which ſpeake ſimply and roundly vnto vs ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the truth of God, then thoſe whiche flatter and ſeduce vs, to pleaſe vs, and keepe themſelues mor at eaſe; for in this diuine court and in theſe laſt appeales, ſentences ſhall not
<pb facs="tcp:4510:24"/> there be weyed in the ballance of carnal ſenſe, &amp; humane reaſon, but in the ballance of Gods worde, which ſhall not be vnderſtoode, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to our fantaſie, but according to the will of the ſpirit of God: then both Clients and aduocates ſhall find them ſelues as much aſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nied the one as the other: and the one ſhall not eaſe then the caſe of the other, for they both ſhalbe ſufficiently troubled eche one with his owne cauſe, the plaintife ſhall not there be on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in danger as in the courtes and iudgements of men, but if he be condemned, the proctor and aduocates ſhalbe ſubiect to the ſame condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation with him, and more greeuous; for if the hearer be condemned, becauſe hee hath taken pleaſure to heare and followe euill councel, much more grieuouſly ſhal the councellour be puniſhed, who hath had more regard to ſatiſfie his couetouſnes, &amp; affectio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of a poore ignora<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t ſoule, then the word of God: for hee hath ſetled him, and confirmed him in errour, whome hee ought to haue w<hi rend="sup">t</hi>drawen fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> errour, &amp; to haue led him into a better way by his good councel.</p>
            <p>Why doe not theſe councellours as well alleadge other places of holy ſcripture, whiche <note place="margin">Sect.</note> be repugnant to the affectio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of man, as they al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leadge thoſe whereby they ſeeke to pleaſe it: for it is not needefull nowe to trauell muche
<pb facs="tcp:4510:24"/> to finde cloking to our fleſh, to arme it againſt truth, to furniſh it with armour, and to put the ſword into her hand to fight againſt it: for ſhe is but too cunning by nature to &amp; bold &amp; haſty to fight againſt her owne ſaluation, and to ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uance her owne deſtructio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: wherfore ſhee hath herein more neede of a bridle then a ſpurre.</p>
            <p>This Satan, that endeuoureth himſelfe ſo <note place="margin">Sect.</note> much to embolden the fleſhe, to defile it ſelfe in Idolatrie and ſuperſtition, is not very haſtye to alleadge vnto it, Abraham and all the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>triarkes and Prophets, who in what place ſo euer they be found, although they haue beene couerſant oftentimes among the Pagans and Idolaters, yet were they neuer partakers of their Idolatrie, but alſo made publike confeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of their religion, and of the true GOD whom they ſerued. Satan and his aduocates y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ſerue him, will know nothing of all that, they paſſe it ouer lightly without making any men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion therof: they haue no care to rehearſe the examples of the fayth and conſtancie of the Hebrewe children, or of Daniell: whereof the one did chooſe rather to be caſt into the fornace of Nabuchadnazar, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to worſhip his image &amp; <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Dan.</hi> 3.</note> to do honour &amp; reuerence to his Idole of gold. The other deſired rather to be caſt into the den &amp; throte of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> lyons, then to remaine onely three <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Dan.</hi> 7.</note>
               <pb facs="tcp:4510:25"/> dayes without praying to God, and without making open confeſſion of him. They can alſo <note place="margin">Exa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ples of the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles and martirs.</note> well deſſemble the example of the Apoſtles &amp; Martyrs, and of ſo many of the good faithful, whiche haue better liked to endure the moſte grieuous torments that Tyrants coulde ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gine, then onely to doe reuerence to an image, or put a little inſenſe vpon the fire before an Idole: if they had knowne how, or would haue deſſembled and halted on both feete, and haue ſerued God and Baal, they had neuer ſuffred a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny thing for Chriſt Ieſus, their blood had not beene ſhed for the teſtimonie of the trueth, and the Churche of Ieſus Chriſt had had no Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyrs.</p>
            <p>I maruell what newe chriſtianitie ſuch men <note place="margin">Sect.</note> will bring vs, and to what ende they thinke Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt hath ſayde: who ſo denyeth mee be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mat.</hi> 10. <hi>Mar.</hi> 8.</note> men, I will denie him before my father &amp; his angels. Who ſo is aſhamed of me and my wordes in this adulterous and ſinfull genera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, I wil be aſhamed of him before my father which is in heauen, and before his holy angels. He y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> is not afraid to leeſe his ſoule, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> is to ſay, his life for my ſake ſhall finde it: hee that con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſeth me before men, I will confeſſe and ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mat.</hi> 16. <hi>Ioh.</hi> 12.</note> him before my father which is in heauen.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:4510:25"/>
            <p>Wee ſee plainely by theſe wordes, that Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Sect.</hi> The faith of a Chriſtia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</note> Chriſt is not contented with a vayne and dead faith, that ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> imagineth himſelf to haue, but requireth a true and liuely fayth, whiche muſt be ſo rooted in the heart that it muſt bring forth her boughes and fruits outward, &amp; what are theſe principall fruites, but that wee make profeſſion of Ieſus Chriſt as well in wordes <note place="margin">The fruits of faith.</note> as workes: but what elſe requireth the Lorde of vs, but onely this ſacrifice of prayſe; when the Prophets do propheſie of the church of our Lord Ieſus Chriſt, what difference ſet they be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene it and other religions, and betweene her ſacrifice and thoſe of the Sinagogue? what is the principall point whereby ſhee may be knowne and ſeparated from others, but the ſacrifice of prayſe? whereby I vnderſtand here all that the faythful ſayth or doth is to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> glorye and praiſe of God: for although that praier bee ſometimes called eſpecially by that name, yet the ſignification thereof ſtretcheth farther, and comprehendeth other things that apperteine to the diuine ſeruice: for the faythfull man doth not his workes whatſoeuer they be, to be iuſtified by them, or to merit by meanes of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, the kingdome of heauen, for it is already meri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes &amp; purchaſed for him, not by his merit but by the merit of Ieſus: and before he was incor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porated
<pb facs="tcp:4510:26"/> into the Church of Ieſus Chriſt, hee was iuſtified by fayth in him: for he was made vnto vs of God, Iuſtice, Wiſedome, Sanctifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation, and redemption, the principall end: the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of the workes of the faythful is to prayſe God, and to giue him laud and thankes for all his be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefites, after the example of Angels, to whom by Ieſus Chriſt hee is aſſociated and conioy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, which neuer ceaſe to prayſe God in all thinges: And yet doe they it not to merit Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>radiſe therby, wherof they haue alreadie y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> fru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>itio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: but becauſe God is their ſoueraigne good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, &amp; alſo mans, and that they are created to that end, as we are: and therefore when Ieſus Chriſt exhorteth his diſciples to good works, and to make their light ſhyne by them before men, he ſayth not to the end, that by them you may be iuſtified, or merit Paradiſe: but to the <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mat.</hi> 5.</note> end that men may ſee them and glorifie your father which is in heauen.</p>
            <p>Seeing the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> it is the propertie of the church <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Sect.</hi> The work of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> church.</note> to offer vnceſſantly to God this ſacrifice of prayſe, how can ſhee without that, be the church of Ieſus Chriſt? Wherefore hath the Apoſtle ſayd, if thou confeſſe the Lord with thy mouth, <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ro.</hi> 10. Faith and confeſſion.</note> and beleeue in thy heart that God hath rayſed him from the dead, thou ſhalt be ſaued: for man beleeueth in the heart to iuſtification, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſeth with mouth to ſaluation. He requireth
<pb facs="tcp:4510:26"/> fayth aboue all thinges, without the which all <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ro.</hi> 14. <hi>Heb.</hi> 11.</note> is but hypocriſie, ſinne, and abhomination: but he requireth alſo confeſſion of the mouth, and the outwarde teſtimonie of this inward fayth, to ſerue to the glory of God, and the edification of our neighbour: we ſee how hee ioyneth the confeſſion of mouth with fayth in hearte; be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they are thinges inſeparable, as the ſoule and life, the fire and his brightnes, the Sonne and his light, the body and his ſhadowe: for if fayth be in heart, there is no doubt, but that Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt dwelleth there by fayth: as Saint <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Eph.</hi> 2.</note> Paule witneſſeth. If Ieſus Chriſte dwelleth there, he is not then without his holy Spirit. But for this cauſe are wee called the temple of God, becauſe God by his holy ſpirit dwelleth in vs. And therfore the Apoſtle ſayth againe, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he which hath not the ſpirit of Chriſt, is not of Chriſt, and cannot be acounted for a Chriſtian. <note place="margin">1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 6. <hi>Sect. Rom.</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note>
            </p>
            <p>Seeing it is thus, howe is it poſſible if God dwel in the heart, that the diuell ſhould be in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> tongue, in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> mouth, in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> hands, &amp; in the other me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>bers, which all take life fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the heart, &amp; are <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iam.</hi> 2.</note> al guided &amp; gouerned therby: S. Iames ſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> tongue ſayth, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> out of one ſpring can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not come ſweete &amp; bitter water, yet this will make vs beleeue the contrary, to the end that that maye bee verefied in them, whiche is ſayde in the ſame place: out of one mouth
<pb facs="tcp:4510:27"/> proceedeth bleſſing and curſing, by the tongue we bleſſe God the father, and by the ſame wee curſe men, which are made to the Image of God. But that which worſt is, wee deny and blaſpheme him, with the tongue and mouth, which he gaue vs to glorifie and confeſſe him: and we make of our members, which ſhould be the weapons of Iuſtice and holyneſſe, the wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pons of vnrighteouſnes and iniquitie. Ieſus Chriſt ſayth that out of the abundance of the hearte, the mouth ſpeaketh; And that the good <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mat.</hi> 12.</note> man out of the good treaſure of his heart, vtte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth good thinges, and the wicked man vtte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth euill thinges. Wherfore by the ſame rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons Ieſus Chriſt conuinceth the Scribes and <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mat.</hi> 12.</note> Phariſees of the malice &amp; peruerſenes of their hearts, &amp; by their own words, ſaying, thou ſhalt be iuſtified, (that is to ſay) knowne to be ſuche as thou art, and be declared iuſt or vniuſt, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demned or abſolued by thy doings and ſayings. For if they had had Ieſus Chriſt in their harts, they had not had Belzebub in their mouths: for as Saint Paule witneſſeth, No man can ſay the Lorde Ieſus, but by the ſpirite of God, no man ſpeaking by the holy Ghoſt, can call Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus <note place="margin">1. Cor. 12. Sect.</note> execrable, nor ſpeake euill of him, nor blaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheme him.</p>
            <p>Wherefore for a full concluſion, if we will
<pb facs="tcp:4510:27"/> of right be counted Chriſtians before God, &amp; before his elect and his Church, it is neceſſary to lay this foundation: that as it is requiſite to haue a true faith planted in heart to be incorpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rated in him and his Churche, ſo muſt we con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe him, otherwiſe what elſe is our fayth, but a dreame, a fantaſie, &amp; a fooliſh imagination of our owne braine: but the faith of a chriſtian, is not onely as a ſpeculatiue knowledge with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out falling to actio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, &amp; putting nothing to effect: for it can be in no place w<hi rend="sup">t</hi>out ſhewing it ſelf, it fareth ſo with it; as Ieremie witneſſeth, that he hath prooued it in the word of God, whiche he willingly ſometimes haue kept in, ſeeing (as ſeemeth to him) that it profited not much, when he vttered it, but that it was had in ſcorne, and he ſet him ſelfe in diſpleaſure and danger of death amongſt the wicked, which were harde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned more and more: therefore he ſaid, I will make no more mention of the Lord and will <note place="margin">The vertue of the word of God &amp; of fayth.</note> ſpeake no more in his name. Then his woorde was in my hearte as a burning fire, ſhut vp in my bones, and I fayled, and was weery with forbearing that I could ſtay no more. He can not reſiſt the ſpirit of God, for the zeale that he hath to the glory of God enflameth him ſo, that he cannot hold his peace. Seeing then that the word of God is ſo veheme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t a fire, wherby faith
<pb facs="tcp:4510:28"/> is enflamed, how is it poſſible, but y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> fla<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>e, light, and heat, or at the leaſt ſome little ſmoke will ſhew forth? for when as fayth is almoſt wholy extinguiſhed, &amp; yet there remaineth ſome little ſpark is it not poſſible, but y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> it wil caſt ſome lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle ſmoke, as y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> flaxe &amp; bra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ds w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> yet ſmoke, whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſt there is yet a little fire, or hath been lately.</p>
            <p>I ſay not this to fauour and ſtir vp more a <note place="margin">Sect.</note> ſort of raſhe and raging ſpirits, which without any wit or diſcretion will counterfeit to be ze<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous profeſſours of the Goſpel, and will ſpeake of all matters, and crie out againſt Idols with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out meaſure, and without ſeeking occaſions &amp; conſidering circumſtances, which ſeeme to e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dification, but ſerue only to trouble the weake, and to put them in danger which truely feare God: and to coulor their fury and madnes, they alleadge the zeale of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Prophets &amp; Apoſtles, &amp; the feruentnes of the ſpirit, which they cannot keepe in: wherein they declare themſelues ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to reſemble that glorious Elihu the Bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zite, who was one of the comforters or rather diſcomforters of Iob, then to Hieremy Anata<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thite, for they vſe the ſame talke, &amp; ſay as hee doth. I am full of wordes, and the ſpirit with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in me, conſtraineth me. Behold my ſtomack is as the wine, which hath no vent, and is as newe veſſels, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> breake. I wil ſpeake therfore &amp; breath my ſelfe. They are like to newe wines, w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> haue
<pb facs="tcp:4510:28"/> not yet wrought, &amp; ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>not be co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>teyned within y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> veſſels, but it breaketh the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> or els muſt haue ve<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t.</p>
            <p>But as the ſpirite of God cannot be Idle in <note place="margin">Sect.</note> mans heart, ſo doth it not enforce man beyonde the bondes of Chriſtian modeſtie: he aloweth not the zeale without ſpirituall knowledge &amp; wiſdome: therfore the Apoſtle ſaith, the ſpirits of the prophets are ſubiect to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> prophets, as he <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rom.</hi> 10. 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 14. <hi>Act.</hi> 9. 13. 19. 21. <hi>Act.</hi> 17.</note> himſelfe hath ſhewed it by experience, for al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though he were excelle<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t in all the giftes of god aboue others, neuertheleſſe he alwayes ſubmit<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ted him ſelfe to the iudgement of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> church, and neuer deſpiſed the cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cell of his brethre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, as it appeareth in y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> which was done in y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> church of Damas, Antioche, Hieruſalem, &amp; Epheſus, &amp; when he was in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> town of Athe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s tarying for Silas &amp; Timotheus, his ſpirit was ſtirred vp in himſelf, ſeeing the town ſo much giue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to ido<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>latry: wherfore he diſputed in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> aſſembly with y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Iewes, and with thoſe that feared God, &amp; eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry day in the marked &amp; publike places, w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> thoſe w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> by chance came vnto him: but hee cried not out in the ſtreetes like a mad man: he cried not againſt the Idols without reaſon, he ran not in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the temples to breake &amp; beate them downe: alſo he went not to doe reuere<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce vnto them, &amp; was wary enough to giue any ſigne either in deede or woorde whereby any mought iudge that hee hadde them in honoure or anye
<pb facs="tcp:4510:29" rendition="simple:additions"/> eſtimation: he made no conſcience to enter into the temples, and to behold their Altars and I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doles; but he we<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t not thither with y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Idolaters, when they made their ſacrifices to pleaſe them, and for feare of offending the Athenians: but contrariwiſe, he went thither to finde occaſion to drawe them from their Idolatrie and ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtition, which he condemned by his publike te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtimonie, but not without great reaſon and chriſtian wiſdome and modeſtie.</p>
            <p>So then as I cannot allowe theſe enuious, <note place="margin">Sect.</note> frantike, &amp; offenſiue perſons: ſo wil I not con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demne all thoſe which ſhewe not the like zeale as Saint Paule did: for I knowe where one may finde ſuch: but I ſpeake eſpecially againſt thoſe wiſe ſpirits which feare ſo greatly to fall into any danger, for the name of Ieſus Chriſt, that they gouerne themſelues ſo warily, that they ſuffer not to paſſe from the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> any little ſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dow of ſmoke, whereby one may iudge y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> there is not one only ſparke of faith in their hearts, for they feare ſo much, that any ſhoulde knowe that there is any fire of the Goſpel in them, that they endeuour by al meanes to put it out, and gouerne themſelues in ſuch ſort, that none of good iudgement can account them other then for enemies of Ieſus Chriſt.</p>
            <p>Ieſus Chriſt taught no ſuche leſſon to his <note place="margin">Sect.</note>
               <pb facs="tcp:4510:29"/> Diſciples: it is neceſſarie if we will followe them, to obey that the Lord commandeth vs by his Prophets. Come out of Babylon, flee from <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Eſa.</hi> 41.</note> the Chaldeans, depart ye, goe out from thence, touch no vncleane thing, goe out of the middeſt of her, be ye cleane, ye that beare the veſſels of the Lord, flye out from the middeſt of Babylon, <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ier.</hi> 51.</note> and deliuer euery man his ſoule. Thinke wee that theſe exhortations are in vayne, and that the holy Ghoſt biddeth ſo often to goe out with out cauſe? Let vs conſider what earneſtnes he vſeth, and if any thinke that ſuch exhortations pertaine not to vs, let him hearke<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to that which the holy Apoſtle ſayth, after he hath declared to the faithfull, that there is no agreement be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene the faythfull and the infidell. Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore departe from the middeſt of them, and ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parate your ſelues from them, ſaith the Lord, and touch not any defiled thing, and I wil re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceaue you, and be your father, and you ſhall be my ſonnes and daughters. Seeing then we haue expreſſe commandement to goe out of Babylon, and to ſeparate our ſelues from Infidels, eyther we muſt doe it, or confeſſe that we reſiſt the will of God, and that we offende him, we cannot reſiſt the expoſition that the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Ghoſt propoſeth ſo plainely. The ſumme is to vnderſtand it well, and to knowe what ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner
<pb facs="tcp:4510:30"/> of departure and ſeparation this ought to be, and then to put it in execution.</p>
            <p>We may goe out from Babylon, and ſepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate <note place="margin">Sect.</note> our ſelues from Infidels, three maner of wayes. The firſt is, in bodie onely, hauing the heart ioyned with them, The ſecond is, in ſpirit onely, hauing the body ioyned with them. The third is, hauing the body and ſpirit both to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether. This laſt departure and ſeparation is the ſureſt for it is very hard, and almoſt vnpoſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible to liue amo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gſt the Babylonians &amp; Egyp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tians, without being defiled w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> their abominati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, or put our ſelues in danger of their ſword: It is very hard to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> fleſh to put it ſelf in da<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ger of the ſword for confeſſion of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> truth, if y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> vertue of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſpirit of God change it not, &amp; vnleſſe it doe ſuch viole<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce to it ſelf to forget &amp; forſake it ſelf, which cannot bee without a ſingular gift of God. On the other ſide, to participate and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent to the abominations of Idolaters, and to pleaſe God, are things too farre contrary, and which cannot agree together: wherefore the Lord hath not without cauſe withdrawen his people from Egypt &amp; from Babylon, &amp; forbid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den that they ſhould make any aliance, neither by marriage, nor any other kinde of way, with Pagans &amp; Idolaters, which were their neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours, <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Exo.</hi> 34. <hi>Deu.</hi> 7.</note> knowing it is very hard to touch pitch
<pb facs="tcp:4510:30"/> without being defiled therwith, and to be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſant <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Eccl.</hi> 13.</note> amo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g thornes w<hi rend="sup">t</hi>out being pricked.</p>
            <p>But I know well that the fleſh can replye <note place="margin">Sect.</note> againſt this councel. Firſt that many ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>not go out though they would: Then there is feare of looſing their earthly goodes, and delightes, &amp; pleaſures of the world, which muſt bee forſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken; and the loue, ſtudie, and care of houſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holdes and families which are committed to our charge: I am not ignorant what tempta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion this may be: And therfore I would not co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrain al thoſe which haue knowledg of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> truth, to go fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> their lands &amp; countries to cary them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues into places, where it is lawful to ſerue God in libertie of the ſpirit, or conde<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ne the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>together, &amp; caſt the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> off as vnworthy to be diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples of Ieſus Chriſt, &amp; to be cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ted for brethre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, and chriſtians, if they did it not: for I knowe well the departure would be very hard to ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny, &amp; that it were impoſſible in this time to find a cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>try of libertie which were able to receiue ſo great a nu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ber of people as God hath ſhewed mercy to, &amp; wherin there were earthly goods ſufficie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t to nouriſh &amp; entertain the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, if god of his grace would not cauſe ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>na to raine down as <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Exo.</hi> 16.</note> he did in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> deſert: yet if it ſhal pleaſe y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Lord to giue ſuch ſtre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gth to thoſe who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he hath viſited by his grace, to depart amo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gſt Idolaters to make
<pb facs="tcp:4510:31"/> their abode there, where there is no conſtraint to commit idolatrie, there is no countrie ſo ſtrait nor ſo ſcarcely victuales nor yet ſo euil prouided of worldly goods, which he cannot en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>large and make able to receiue all thoſe, which wil come thither, and furniſh them with what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer is neceſſary for them.</p>
            <p>He coulde as eaſily finde meanes to do this <note place="margin">Sect.</note> as he did to giue ſo commodious an habitation, and ſo apt a lodging, and place to Noah and al <note place="margin">Gen. 7. Noahs ark.</note> his familie, and to all the beaſts which entered in with him into his Arke, within ſo weake a veſſell, and which according to mans reaſon, was nothing able to receaue ſo many creaturs with victuals neceſſary for the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. Who made the Arke ſo well able to receaue, ſo ſtable, and ſo ſtrong? who made the victuals which were therein, to encreaſe and multiply, but onely faith? If then we ſhut our eyes as Noah did, to follow the Lord, we ſhall alway finde the arke large enough, and ſufficiently prouided. The Lord whom we ſeeke and are willing to ſerue, hath ſufficiently declared vnto vs ſince the cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ation of the world, what care he had ouer vs, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen to prouide for vs in all our neceſſities: For before he had created ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, he prepared his lodg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing for him throughly garniſhed, not onely for things which were neceſſary for him, but for al
<pb facs="tcp:4510:31"/> thinges that he could deſire, to the ende that nothing might be wanting to him, wherby he might take his ful pleaſure vpon earth, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in he would place him. Then if this good God hath ſo prepared this lodging for man before he placed him in the world, and would not cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ate him vntill he had firſt created the heauen and earth, the Sea, and all thinges contayned therein, to ſerue him: Thinke we that he hath not now as great care ouer vs, as he had then, and that he cannot as well prepare vs dwel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling places, whereſoeuer it pleaſeth him to di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rect vs, when it pleaſeth him to drawe vs out of a captiuitie, and furniſh them with all thinges neceſſary for vs? Who prouided for the chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren of Iſrael, when they went out of Egypt? Who made them inheritors of the land of their enemies?</p>
            <p>We cannot and the worſt fall, finde a coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trie <note place="margin">Sect.</note> more barre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the deſert of the Iſraelites, after they departed out of the fruitefull land of Egypt: but if many of the Iſraelites, being al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>readie acquainted with the Babylonians, liked rather to tary in Babylon, yea, after they had leaue to returne into their owne countrey, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to leaue their poſſeſſions and delightes y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> they had there, to returne to Hieruſalem; how ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Succeſſours thinke we they may haue at
<pb facs="tcp:4510:32"/> this day amongeſt vs? And therefore I knowe I ſhould profit nothing to exhort al to goe out. Moreouer it were to ſmall purpoſe to ſepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate our ſelues corporally from Idolatrie, &amp; to withdraw our bodies from Egypt, if with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all we withdraw not the heart and minde, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nouncing the maners &amp; faſhions of the Egyp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tians: for it is all one in what ſoyle ſoeuer we be, if we cary the leauen of Egypt with vs, for it were much better to be a true Iſraelite, &amp; to worſhip God purely in the land of Egypt, then to be an Egyptian and Idolater in the deſert, or in the land of Chanaan, and there to worſhip the golden calues, and to take thought for the leekes, the onions, the fleſhe, the fiſhe, &amp; the pottes of Egypt, it were better to call vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the name of God in Egypt, and patiently to abide the tyrannie of Pharaoh, then to be from thence and murmure againſt God, and blaſpheme him, as theſe old Idolaters, Iſra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lites by name, and Egyptians in deede, hauing the body without, and the hearte in Egypt: as at this day it falleth out in manye. We haue knowne ſome, that haue boldly gone out of Egypt, as the monkes goe out of the worlde, They forſake the landes, the countries, the townes and the people of the worlde and of E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gypt, but they forſake neither the worlde nor
<pb facs="tcp:4510:32"/> Egypt, but cary it alwayes with them. They doe in deede put off their garmentes, and put on other: But they put not off their monkery and the old man, to put on the new man. They cannot change their old Egyptian, and Egyp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tian ſkinne. They cannot forget Sodome and Gomorrhe, nor put the hande to the Plough, without looking backe as Lots wiſe did.</p>
            <p>Manye of theſe are not counted to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turne into Egypt, but doe their endeuour to <note place="margin">Sect.</note> draw others backe thither, and to keepe them there ſtill, as the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ies, whiche were ſent to ſpy out the land of Chanaan: we are not igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant of the reportes which ſome make of coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tries here about, wee deny not but there are great faultes and great imperfections in ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny, which boaſt themſelues of the Goſpell: but we woulde alſo that theſe delicate Iſraelites did vnderſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d, that in going out of Egypt they muſt paſſe the Sea, and through the deſert, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore they come to the land of Chanaan: and y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> fleſhe ſhall not finde there all that it deſireth. It muſt firſt beare &amp; ſuffer muche, &amp; enter into great dangers? theſe delicate chriſtia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s ought to think y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> they goe from among men, to liue a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt other men, &amp; not among angels: for if we will finde out angels and liue among the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, we muſt goe ſeek them in Paradiſe, and not in
<pb facs="tcp:4510:33"/> this corruptible earth.</p>
            <p>Yet what vice or imperfection ſoeuer there be <note place="margin">Sect.</note> in them, which be gone out of Egypt, &amp; are in a countrey of libertie, yet this good they haue moreouer and beſides, which is not ſmall: that it is lawfull for all them (to whome GOD hath giuen ſuch grace) to be good men, which they may be without danger of their life, which is not lawfull euery where: for the greateſt faulte that is at this day in the world, and the greateſt danger is to be a good man, and to be deſirous to liue in the feare of God: if there be Egyptians mingled among the Iſraelites, yea though y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> number be great, yet is it no ſmal be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefit of God to haue libertie to heare his word, and to ſerue him according to the ſame with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out feare and moleſtation of Pharaoh.</p>
            <p>Wherfore I iudge it moſt ſafetie for them, <note place="margin">Sect.</note> which are yet in Egypt, to go out fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>together both corporally and ſpiritually if it poſſible, &amp; if they haue any good opportunity to doe ſo: but I aduiſe them not to departe thence in body; if the heart renounce not the ſame al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>together, it were better the bodye ſhoulde re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maine there together with the heart, then to doe as many doe, which are come to theſe partes, and haue begunne to murmure, when as they haue not found (not water as
<pb facs="tcp:4510:33"/> the Iſraelites in the deſert:) But Malmeſey, or Ipocrys, Quailes, Partriges, &amp; a couered table: there come many which giue vs great &amp; horrible offences, &amp; commit execrable villa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies vnworthie, not only for Chriſtians, but for Turkes and Paganes: and then they com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaine of the hardnes and barbarouſnes of the people, which they haue found here, and ſlan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the land wherein God is glorified. If they haue found the people hard &amp; ſtiffnecked, they haue made them worſe vnto vs, and more ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinate by their offences; and then to excuſe the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſelues they lay the burden on others.</p>
            <p>I ſay not this that I woulde excuſe the <note place="margin">Sect.</note> ingratitude, and barbarouſnes amongeſt vs, which doth greatly diſpleaſe me. I wil not de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie, but that there is little feare of God, fayth, charity, and amendment of life in many, which giueth cauſe of offence euen to the beſt ſorte: that which I ſayd, I ſay to this ende, that thoſe which are well minded ſhould not lightly be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeue all euill reportes, and ſhoulde not refuſe through them to goe out of Egypt, if GOD graunt them opportunitie: and let them not caſt their eye vpon them, for they haue not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiued the Goſpel for their ſakes, but that they ſhould haue a regard to Ieſus Chriſt whome they ſerue, who wil not offend them, if they be
<pb facs="tcp:4510:34"/> his diſciples: for euen as the good cannot alto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether eſchewe the euill, but that they ſhall finde of them in euerye place, if they departe not out of the world: euen ſo thoſe which haue the feare of God cannot be there where Chriſt is purely preached, but they ſhall finde their like, at the leaſt, the wicked that be there cannot hynder them from beeing good and ſeruing of God, if they haue a deſire thereto: which they cannot be ſuffered to doe there, where it is he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſie and a greater offence, then murther to confeſſe Ieſus Chriſt, as it behooueth a good Chriſtian.</p>
            <p>Wherefore I thinke as I haue alreadie <note place="margin">Sect.</note> ſayd, that this departure out of Babylon, which is done both in body and ſoule, is the moſt ſure and happy. For it is no ſmal good to be co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>uer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſant with the faithfull at their publike pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers and preaching of the worde of God, and at the partaking of the Sacraments; as wee may eaſily knowe by the great deſire that Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uid had, to ſee the arke of the Lorde, &amp; to praiſe him in his holy hill, and his tabernacle, with his choſen people. Why doeth he lament ſo much for the tabernacles of the Lorde? Yea, why doeth he crye with ſo great affection, O Lord how amyable are thy tabernacles? what
<pb facs="tcp:4510:34"/> loue is it that I beare to them? he was a pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet, he was not conſtrained to commit Idola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trie: what griefe ſuſteyneth he, when as he is purſued by his enemies, and is ſeparated from the church of God bodely? although he coulde not be ſeparated ſpiritually? for he was better there being in the houſe of Achis, then Saule and all his enemies, which were bodely in the middeſt of the common weale and Churche of Iſrael: yet howe doeth it grieue him, that hee cannot prayſe God in the place that hee hath choſen with his people? although he ceaſed not to prayſe him alwayes where he was, and ſing Pſalmes vnto him? But he was not ignorant what fauour and goodneſſe God ſheweth tow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ardes his people, when they are aſſembled in his name: hee had had ſufficiently tryed, howe the vertue of the holy Ghoſt doeth ſhewe forth it ſelfe in theſe holy aſſemblies, and in this bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy of Ieſus Chriſt vnited together with his members corporally and ſpiritually, to glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie him all with one heart and voyce: why doe the poore captiues of Babylon ſo muche la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment Hieruſalem, but becauſe they feele what a plague it is to bee ſo oppreſſed by tyran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie, that men cannot haue anye good fourme of a Churche, nor yet ſerue
<pb facs="tcp:4510:35"/> God according to his pollicie and ordinances, nor make publike confeſſion and profeſſion thereof as the faithfull deſire.</p>
            <p>But becauſe it is hard for all men to be a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble <note place="margin">Sect.</note> to come to his felicitie, to depart wholy this day out of Egypt and Babylon both cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porally and ſpiritually to liue in libertie: yet at the leaſt it is neceſſarie to depart thence in heart and minde, if they cannot get thence in body: and how can this departure and ſepara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion be, if we keepe not our ſelues from the fil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thines and abominations of this worlde; for that it is the true religion, as Saint Iames witneſſeth. He that liueth amongſt the Idola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters and communicateth not with their Idola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tries and ſinnes, he is much better ſeparated from them, then he that is conuerſant with the Godly, and hath his heart repleniſhed with ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perſtition and hypocriſie, for this ſeparation is made by the holy Ghoſt; who ſeparateth the elect and children of God, from the wicked and reprobate, and ſanctifieth and dedicateth them to ſerue for his honour and glory, for this cauſe y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> chriſtia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s are called ſaints, &amp; confeſſe y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> holy vniuerſall Church. Seeing then that the Church is holy, &amp; that it is nothing elſe but the aſſemblie and companie of the faithful, it follo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>weth neceſſarily that al the faithfull, which are
<pb facs="tcp:4510:35"/> the members whereof this body conſiſteth, and that this co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pany aſſembled and made bee holy: for this cauſe we call it alſo the communion of Saintes. And S. Paule writing to the faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full which haue receiued the Goſpell, he ſalu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth them, and called them Saintes, as it ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peareth in all his Epiſtles: for what cauſe then are they called Saintes, but becauſe they are ſeparated from all prophane vſes, and that they are drawen away from the ſeruice of the Diuell, the world, &amp; the fleſhe; &amp; that they are wholy dedicated, conſecrated, and ſanctified to god to ſerue him only? for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſcripture calleth y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> thing holy, which is ſecluded from all other vſe, and which is nothing but to the ſeruice of God, and therefore the Lord called his people <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Leui.</hi> 19. 1. <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.</note> Iſraell, the holy people, and commanded them to ſanctifie them ſelues, ſaying be yee holy, for I am holy.</p>
            <p>For this cauſe he hath ſeparated and diui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded them from all other people, and hath giuen <note place="margin">Sect.</note> them lawes, ordina<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ces, and ceremonies, cleane vnlike to all other people, to keepe them bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter in his ſeruice, to this ende y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> they might not be defiled nor polluted with the ſuperſtitions, Idolatries, and abominations of others: wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore he hath endeuoured by all meanes to draw them from all companie and acquaintance
<pb facs="tcp:4510:36"/> with Idolaters, which might any way induce them to worſhip ſome other beſides him ſelfe, or in other ſort then hee had commanded: if it were all one, &amp; that it were no ſinne to be in company with Idolaters, and to communicate with them in their ſacrifices &amp; abominations, what neede was there that God ſhould giue a Lawe? to what purpoſe hath he ſo charged the people of Iſrael with ceremonies, if it were lawfull for them to vſe al indifferently as they lifted? why did Moſes ſtudy all that he could, (being thereto appointed of god) to ordaine the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ceremonies <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>lat diſſona<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t &amp; contrary to al their neyghbours about them, &amp; al the Pagans &amp; I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dolaters? It was for nothing els, but that firſt y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Lord would foreſee by this way, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> they ſhould haue no acquaintance and familiaritie with them in that which concerned the ſeruice of God, nor any ſimilitude, wherby they might be induced to follow them or obey them, with ſuch an opinion of falſe Gods as the Pagans haue. Then to the end it ſhould not ſeeme they did like vnto them, &amp; that y<hi rend="sup">t</hi>, which they did to the honour of their God, was done to the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour of ſtrange Gods: or y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> it might not ſeeme, that therby they did allow their manner of dea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling: ſo farre is it y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> God would permit it to be lawfull for the people of Iſrael to communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cate with the blaſphemies, ſacriledges, &amp; abo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minations
<pb facs="tcp:4510:36"/> of Idolaters; that he would not ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer them only to haue any agreement with the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in ceremonies, &amp; in their maner of doings w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: he would not ſuffer them to haue ſo much as in the outward thinges, euen thoſe which o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe might haue beene indifferent &amp; law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful: why did he forbid this ſo ſharply, but for the cauſes aboue ſayd, &amp; to keepe his people al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waies y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> better w<hi rend="sup">t</hi>out wa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dering fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> his ſeruice.</p>
            <p>Wherfore if we wilbe accounted Gods peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Sect.</hi> The office of Gods people.</note> we muſt be holy both in body &amp; ſoule, &amp; wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes by our words &amp; works, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> we are his chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, &amp; that y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> works of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> wicked diſpleaſe vs, or at the leaſt y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> wee allowe them not: for whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Apoſtle forbiddeth vs to be partakers of the works of darknes, &amp; co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mandeth vs rather to reproue the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, he doth ſufficiently ſhew vs, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> wee cannot be childre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of light, if we do not wholy renounce darknes, &amp; y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> we ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>not be ſeparated fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Idolaters &amp; Infidels, if we co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>fourme our ſelues to their maners, their works, &amp; co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>uerſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. And therfore for a man to boaſt himſelf to be faithful, &amp; outwardly to allow idolatrie, &amp; to giue good cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tena<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce to idolatries are things w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>not agree together in a true ſerua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of god. Let vs not think our ſelues excuſed before god, <note place="margin">Sect.</note> nor in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſcie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of thoſe w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> are faithful indeed in ſaying: I know wel enough, what my heart is, what cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tena<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce ſoeuer I cary, or what godly
<pb facs="tcp:4510:37"/> ſhew ſoeuer I make, yet put I no truſt neither haue I any deuotion in Idoles, but I worſhip y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> onely God in my heart, it is better yet to doe thus, then to perſecute the truth, and for a man to ſhewe himſelfe an open enemie vnto God. But yet it is impoſſible that the heart ſhould be free from Idolatrie, when al the body is de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>filed, and doth reuerence vnto ſtrange Gods, &amp; to the enemie of God: what good heart ſoeuer a ſubiect can beare to his prince, yet could not the prince beare it, that he ſhould do homage to another, &amp; that he ſhould cary weapon againſt his natural prince. Men ſay commonly that he y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſweareth by art, for ſweareth him ſelfe by art; we ought not to thinke that the heart remai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth vnſworne, if the tongue forſweare it ſelf; for we muſt vnderſtand the othe according to the meaning of him that giueth it, and not after the meaning of him that receiueth it. And when we are partakers of the ceremonies, ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifices and Sacraments, whether they be of the faithful or infidels, we bynde our ſelues &amp; ſweare vnto that religion, by which we com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municate with them.</p>
            <p>We haue then trimly ſayde that our mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning is farre other, for God alloweth no So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phiſtrie: he ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>not cal things by but their name: fraude and deceit is ſomewhat more honeſt a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongeſt
<pb facs="tcp:4510:37"/> men, then manifeſt thefte, yet is it ac<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>counted before God for theft in deede, what name ſo euer men giue it: wherfore let vs not thinke that by our goodlie ſhewes, our Idola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try is ſo excuſed, that it is not Idolatrye, and a true kinde of renouncing Chriſt Ieſus: although it ſeme to vs ſomewhat more alowa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, then to deny him openly. S. Peter denyed Chriſt with his mouth, he ſaid, he was none of his, and do wee make anie more of him? what ſpeech do our works vtter els but the ſame of S. Peter? where vnto tendeth our Idolatries and outward hipocryſies? but to let Infidels vnderſtand that wee are not the Diſciples of Chriſt Ieſus, &amp; that we know neither him nor his Goſpel.</p>
            <p>To replie, that we do it not with the hart, but <note place="margin">Sect.</note> the heart is farre otherwiſe: So was euen the heart of S. Peter: it grieued him greatly to deny Chriſt Ieſus, but the infirmitie of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> fleſh &amp; feare of death ouercame the chriſtian conſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie, which ought to haue bene in him, yet can we not excuſe him, but that he ſinned greatlie, and we are leſſe to bee excuſed then he: for he denyed not Ieſus Chriſt for feare of looſing his worldly goodes, or for any light cauſe as we cuſtomablie doe, but for feare of death, he went not to preſent him ſelfe willingly to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounce
<pb facs="tcp:4510:38"/> him as we doe, he went not to the By<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops houſes, nor to the high Prieſtes of the Lawe to pleaſe them, or other of the Iewes; or to make them beleeue he was of their com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany, or that he had no acquaintance or famili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aritie with Ieſus, as they doe, which frequent the temples of Idols; he went thither to ſtand faythfully vnto him, as he had promiſed, &amp; for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> loue and affection he bare to him, yet was hee caught: and ſeeing how his maiſter was hand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led amongſt the murderers, and veiwing the place where he was, fearing death, which was manifeſtly before his face, &amp; was ouercome by the infirmitie of his fleſh: for he was ſo troubled y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he knewe not what he ſayd or did, for that hee ſaw not Ieſus Chriſt then, but as a poore miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable creature, forſake<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of al men, for he had not yet ſuch knowledg of his diuinitie, nor had not receiued the holy Ghoſt ſo abundantly as he had after.</p>
            <p>But we that confeſſe Ieſus Chriſt to be ſet <note place="margin">Sect.</note> at the right hand of God his father, aboue al y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> heauens, we tary not till our aduerſarie vrge vs and preſſe vpon vs, and y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> tyrants conſtraine vs to renounce him, but imediatly of our own accord, &amp; voluntarily we go to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> aſſemblies of Idolaters to the ſame purpoſe, knowing well
<pb facs="tcp:4510:38"/> that we muſt needes diſhonour Ieſus Chriſt with them: &amp; howe much y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> more they marke &amp; behold vs, ſo much y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> more we ſhew our ſelues plentifull in all kindes of blaſphemies &amp; Ido<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latries. There is not ſo ſmal an Idol wheru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>to we do not reuerence, wherunto we do not bow the knee, fearing to be accounted true ſcholers of Chriſt Ieſus.</p>
            <p>The auncient chriſtians did ſo lightly e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteem <note place="margin">Sect.</note> theſe matters as we do, but they thought it ſo vile, ſo deteſtable, &amp; vnworthie a thing for a chriſtian, that hardly they would account the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> for brethren &amp; chriſtians, which had not beene conſtant in the torments, and which liked bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter to forſake and forſweare Chriſt Ieſus, then to ſuffer death, at the leaſt thoſe; which accoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted their life more deare to them then the glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of Ieſus Chriſt, hardly could they euer bee receiued into the miniſterie of the Goſpel: yet was it ſufficient to the Idolaters and Infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dels, that thoſe whom they perſecuted for chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians, ſhould make onely the leaſt ſhewe onely in the world to allow their doings, and to ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour their Idols by outward tokens: they ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red not what the heart was, ſo that they might onely draw one woorde from their mouthes, or cauſe them to ſhewe foorth ſome ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſture, whiche they might drawe to theyr
<pb facs="tcp:4510:39"/> aduantage to boaſt that they had made them to abiure.</p>
            <p>But the fleſhe wil replie, that if it ſhould do o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe, <note place="margin">Sect.</note> it ſhould put it ſelf in danger of being perſecuted, &amp; to cauſe others to be perſecuted, &amp; ſhould ſtir vp great offences. Neere are goodly reaſons of mans wiſedome, and very fit for the fleſhe, and the ſchoole from whence they pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceede, I am in co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pany of Adulterers, which go into a brothell houſe and fearing to offende them, I enter in with them to keepe them com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panie. But ſome will replie againe that the Brothell houſe, and Idoles temple is not al one, but much worſe: for what is Idolatrie and ſuperſtition elſe, but adultery and fornication with ſtra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge gods, &amp; y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ples of Idols, what are they els but brothel houſes of Sathan? wherin we violate the fayth promyſed to our Lord Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt, and wherin we giue our ſelues o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer as whooremongers and adulterers vnto ſtrange Goddes, and to the Diuel as to our lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers? I knowe not howe wee maye ſpeake this more ciuilly, if we will not correct the ſpeech, which the ſpirit of GOD hath vttered by his Prophets, whiche commonly vſe theſe <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Exo.</hi> 16.</note> kinde of ſpeeches, when they preache a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaynſt the Idolatrye of the chyldren of Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raell.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:4510:39"/>
            <p>But a man may yet reply. Although the body be there, yet we conſent not in heart, and yet we auoyde offence and perſecution. Dina the daughter of Iacob, whom the Sonne of the king of Sichem rauiſhed, conſented not in heart to the wickednes of the adulterer, yet was ſhee not altogether without faulte, ſhe was for all that corrupted and counted for an harlot; for if ſhe had remayned in her fathers houſe without wandering abrode to go ſee the daughters of the countrie, ſhe might haue auoi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded that great inconuenience, whereby ſhe fell into great diſhonour and was cauſe of great euill.</p>
            <p>Which of vs all would be content, if his wife <note place="margin">Sect.</note> after ſhee had yeelded her body to an adulterer, ſhould make him this anſweare, ſaying: al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though he had his pleaſure of me, yet was it againſt my will; but becauſe I ſaw my ſelfe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt adulterers, fearing to be ſpoiled, &amp; that they woulde cut my Purſe, or take awaye my Gowne or my Kercheife, I conſented to their will, but I did it vnwillingly, to auoyde that they might doe me no diſpleaſure, and for the feare I had to offend and anger them. Had not the huſband good cauſe to ſay, what hadſt thou to doe in the brothels houſe? why wenteſt thou thither? had not it been better for thee to
<pb facs="tcp:4510:40"/> haue loſt all y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> thou haddeſt, all thy Iewelles, thy rayment, yea, thy lyfe, then thy chaſtitie &amp; ſoule, and to offend God; who commandeth vs to chooſe rather to dye, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to breake his co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandement, &amp; violate y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> fayth &amp; loyaltie, which thou haddeſt promiſed to thy huſband.</p>
            <p>As for that which ſome alleadg alſo concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning offence. Such diſputers ſhew wel that <note place="margin">Sect.</note> they vnderſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d not, or wil not vnderſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d what an offence ſignifieth. For after that maner that they would auoyde offence, they declare that they vnderſtand by offence, the diſfauour that one may haue of men for that he doth, and the diſpleaſure they may haue thereby: but if wee marke well in what ſence the name of offence is taken in the holy ſcriptures, we ſhall finde it ſignifieth nothing els, but all hinderance, that we may giue to our brother by our euill exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple to make him ſtumble and wander out of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> right way of ſaluation, or that we may take of others: for if we will take all that for offence, which men wilbe diſpleaſed at, wee can neuer ſerue God as we ought to do. For as S. Paul ſaith: If we ſhoulde pleaſe men, we coulde not <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Gala.</hi> 1.</note> be the ſerua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts of God. The offence then which we ought to feare, it is all let that we may put either to our ſaluation, or to the ſaluation of our brother. If the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> I enter into y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> brothel houſe <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mat.</hi> 18.</note> with whoremongers, &amp; fearing to offend them
<pb facs="tcp:4510:40"/> commit wickednes amongſt them, I giue two offe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ces in ſteede of auoyding one. Firſt, in that by my diſſimulation or agreement, I allowe iniquitie, and in allowing it, yeeld my ſelfe per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taker therof &amp; faultie: for thoſe ſinne not only, which commit a wicked act, but thoſe which in any ſort conſent therto &amp; allow it, and after y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> fort ſuch a one is an offence to himſelfe; where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by he ſheweth not to haue well vnderſtood &amp; co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſidered that which Ieſus Chriſt ſaith. If thy eye, thy hand, or thy foote offend thee: that is to <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mat.</hi> 5.</note> ſay. If there be any thing which hindereth thy ſaluatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, ſeeing it ought to be as deare &amp; as pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious and neceſſarie as thine eyes, thy hand, or thy feet, cut &amp; pul away al that, &amp; looſe it rather then wholy to periſh. Further he is offe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> wicked, whom he doth more confirme in their iniquitie, for inſteede of reprehending of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to drawe the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> out of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame, they defend the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues by him, &amp; by him take occaſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to approoue it. Thirdly he offendeth the faythfull, &amp; chiefly y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> weake: for whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> they ſee him in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> brothel houſe &amp; with Idolaters, although his heart be farre otherwiſe, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he ſheweth himſelf outwardly: yet they y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ſee him &amp; co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſider his outward works they are troubled therwith in conſcience, and are led by his example, eyther to doe the like, thinking y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> to be wel done, or to accou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t him for a wicked perſon, and ſo they cannot but
<pb facs="tcp:4510:41"/> but to be offended eyther one way or other, for a man cannot iudge of my heart according to my fancie, but he will iudge thereof according to his owne, and according to the teſtimonie, I giue him by my workes: And whatſoeuer I thinke, I cannot binde my neyghboure to my thought, and cannot enforce him to iudge other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe then he ſeeth. And to thinke me a ſheepe when hee ſeeth mee clothed in a Wolfes ſkinne.</p>
            <p>For this cauſe S. Paule admoniſheth vs, <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Sect.</hi> 8. <hi>Theſ.</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> that we ſhould not onely keepe our ſelues fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> euill, but from all ſhew and appearance of euil. Alſo for that cauſe he reproued y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Corinthians, who did eate fleſh offred vnto Idols, although the thing were indifferent of it ſelfe, and of it ſelfe was not euill, as is Idolatrie, which in no ſort can be good: for we cannot commit it, but we muſt deny Ieſus Chriſt. S. Paule re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prooued not the Corinthians, for hauing ſacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficed in the Idol temples with Idolaters, for that was to intollerable for a Chriſtian; but he reprooueth them onely, for that they bought in the ſhambles, and did eate at the tables of I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dolaters the fleſhe that had beene offred to I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dols; It is almoſt, as if now we ſhould buy the candles of that good Saint, not to offer them vp to Idols, but to light vs, as if wee ſhoulde
<pb facs="tcp:4510:41"/> light our ſelues by others, or as if wee ſhoulde buy bread hallowed by the Prieſtes, or of their hallowed candles, to ſerue our turne in the houſe like others without any ſuperſtition, or as if we ſhould go banket at a frier houſe, pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared for the honour of ſome Saint, with the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther friers, &amp; yet not doe it for any deuotion we bare to the Saint: the Corinthians did it not for deuotion, nor for any confidence they had in the Idols, nor yet to make the Idolaters beleeue, that they did any thing honour or re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerence them, that they might the better be a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt them they did not that for anye re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, nor as a Diuine ſeruice, but they did it to ſerue their neceſſities of their bodies, and as a ciuile thing: wherefore as touching them ſelues, and their owne con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience, they ſinned not before God, nor agaynſt the firſt table, yf there were no other reſpect but to them only, but becauſe their worke be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>came offe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce to their neighbours, they ſinned a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt their neighboure, &amp; againſt the ſecond table, &amp; by conſequent againſt the firſt table: againſt Ieſus Chriſt, &amp; againſt God, who will that we ſhould ſerue to his glorie, &amp; to the cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie of our neighboure, which is ioyned there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with.</p>
            <p>Theſe then offended not God in vſing their
<pb facs="tcp:4510:42"/> chriſtian libertie, knowinge that that fleſhe did not differ from the other, ſeeing they nothing eſteemed the Idole. But they offended him in that they abuſed this libertie to the offence of the ſimple, the ignorant, and the weake, whom they enforced to do thinges contrarie to their conſcience: for amonge the Chriſtians, which were at Corinthus, there were ſome of them more ignorant then others: And therefore they were not all yet well reſolued in the matter of Chriſtian libertie; for there were, which made conſcience, to eate fleſhe that had bene offered to Idols: becauſe they had learned by the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell, that Idoles, and the ſeruice to Idols, was forbidden of God, and it ſeemed vnto them, that ſince the ſeruice of Idoles was ſo diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleaſing to God, then they might in no wiſe vſe that, which was once conſecrated to Idols. It was the like caſe, as if nowe wee ſhoulde make conſcie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce to vſe the goods of the church, and other things which were dedicated by our Anceſtours to Idols and their temples: for although idols diſpleaſe God, it followeth not therfore that I cannot applie to better vſe, that, which the ignorant and Idolaters haue abuſed about Idols; and therefore thoſe whiche had more vnderſtanding of chriſtian libertie, amo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g the Corinthians, made no conſcience to vſe thoſe things which were offered vnto Idols:
<pb facs="tcp:4510:42"/> for they did it not for honour to the Idols, nor for any opinion they had in the Idols; for they knewe well that the Idole was nothing, but in the imagination of him y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> thought it ſomwhat: wherefore the Idole was nothing to the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> which had this vnderſtanding, &amp; were deliuered from the errours and fooliſh opinion and imagina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of Idolaters, &amp; therfore the Idol, nor y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> foo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ceit, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> Idolaters had of their idols, could not let the faythfull fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vſing the good crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures of God, but the ignorant which among y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> chriſtians vnderſtood not that point ſo well as others. And therefore it ſeemed to them, they could not vſe any thing that had beene dedica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to Idols: but they ſhoulde teſtifie they did ſome reuerence to the Idols, and ſerue them: wherefore they made conſcience therof, &amp; did eate of that fleſh in doubt, by reaſon of their ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norance. This doubt &amp; ignorance is y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> infirmi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, which S. Paule ſpeaketh of in this place, but whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> theſe ignora<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t ſaw others eate of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> fleſh they were mooued by their exa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ple to eate ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of as well as they, with this doubt &amp; ſcruple of co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſcience, wherin they offe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded God: for ſeeing they doubted, there was no faith, but there was conte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pt of God, ſeeing they did it againſt their conſcience, what ignora<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce ſoeuer there were: And therfore S. Paule reproueth them that were the cauſe thereof.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:4510:43"/>
            <p>Moreouer, wherefore did S. Paule re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prooue <note place="margin">Sect.</note> S. Peter in Antioch before all that were preſent, for that he diſſembled to eate fleſh with the Gentiles, when he ſaw the Iewes en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter which came from Hieruſalem: to eate fleſh and not to eate is a thing indifferent: and ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore S. Peter made it no conſcience to eate fleſhe with the Gentiles, but fearing to offend the Iewes which were weake, and which vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtood not yet that libertie, he withdrew him ſelfe from the table ſeeming not to eate: wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore S. Paule reproued him openly, although S. Peter did the ſame to a good intent, and for feare to offend, for in thinking to auoyd the of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fending of the Iewes, he offended the Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiles with an offence much more dangerous: for inſteede of withdrawing the Iewes from their Iudaiſme, he enduced the gentiles to play the Iewes by his example, and troubled their conſcience.</p>
            <p>Then let vs conſider if the holye Apoſtle <note place="margin">Sect.</note> coulde not allowe in theſe things indifferent, that the faithfull ſhould vſe their libertie with good conſcience, as touching them ſelues, if therby they haue giuen any cauſe of offence to the weake to confirme them in any ſuperſtiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, or to ſtirre them vp to doe any thing a<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>gainſt their conſcience, howe he would permit
<pb facs="tcp:4510:43"/> that thoſe, which went them ſelues to be of the faithfull ſhould offend God, and their neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boure in thinges which are not indifferent, but altogether contrarie to the commandement of God, and much more execrable then one would thinke as he manifeſtly ſheweth: for he hath ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther forbidden in his Law Idolatrie, and the honour and reuerence, which is done to Ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges then he hath done murder and adulterie.</p>
            <p>Then if Saint Paule hath reprooued and <note place="margin">Sect.</note> conde<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ned the Corinthians, who by their know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge and example in abuſing their libertie li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cenciouſly haue giuen occaſion to the ignora<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t to eate fleſh ſacrificed vnto Idols with ſcruple and doubt of conſcience: what would he ſay of thoſe, which giue not onely occaſion to others to honour and reuerence Idols againſt their conſcience, but doe leade them to doe ſo, both by their doctrine and example? For to eate fleſhe then offred to Idoles, as if one ſhoulde eate other fleſhe, without hauing other opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of Idols then the faythfull haue, was not ſinne in it ſelfe, to him that vſed it in that ſort, but it was ſinne to the ignorant and weake chriſtians: which vnderſtood not as yet their li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bertie, who did eate thereof not to ſuch intent as Idolaters, which did eate thereof for honour to their idols but did eat therof with ſcruple of
<pb facs="tcp:4510:44"/> of conſcience fearing thereby to offende God. There was then no ſin in the vſage of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> thing, as in it ſelfe, but y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> themſelues brought therto by their ignorance, and the doubt in conſcience they did put therin; for ſeeing they thought that fleſhe and meate vncleane and defiled, although of it ſelfe, it were pure and cleane to the faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, which accounted it ſo, yet to them, was it polluted and vncleane, for it was not purified to them by the word of God, without the which euerie thing is vncleane to vs: ſeeing they were not yet well aſſured thereby, that they might eate therof without offending God, ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that aſſurance did fayle them, which they could not haue, but by the word of God: it follo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>weth that that they did, was not done in fayth, and co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſequently that it was ſinne: for what ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>euer is done without fayth is ſinne, and what ſoeuer is done without ſtedfaſt aſſurance of the woorde of GOD, with doubt of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience, is done without fayth: wherefore fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing the doctrine of S. Paule, wee cannot deny, but that is ſinne: for the faythfull ought to doe nothing, nor take any thing in hande, whereof he is not playnly reſolued and aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red by the word of God, otherwiſe he ſinneth: and therefore thoſe, whiche knowing the libertie they hadde to eate of that fleſh,
<pb facs="tcp:4510:44"/> fleſhe, were cauſe by their example, that the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers did eate thereof with that doubt they had therein, they were cauſe that theſe ſinned in that: they which had the knowledge of their libertie, had not ſinned, if that they had not in that point beene an offence to the others: y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> is, if they had not emboldened them to eate a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt their conſcience of that meate, whereof they ſtood in doubt: but thoſe, that doe encou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage others to communicate with Idolaters, they doe much worſe without compariſon, for that Idolatrie, whiche they commit, cannot be accounted as a thing indifferent, neither to them that haue knowledg nor to the ignorant, neither do I thinke, that a man, who hath the knowledge of the goſpel, how little ſo euer it be, can communicate there without ſcruple of conſcie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce: thoſe the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> which induce them thither, are they not offenſiue to them?</p>
            <p>And if theſe outward adorations and hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pocriſies <note place="margin">Sect.</note> were indifferent, and lawfull for Chriſtians to vſe, the children of the hebrewes and Daniell alſo had bene very raſhe and ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinate Fooles, yf to ſaue their lyues, they woulde not haue fayned to obeye the kinges commaundemente, as others did, to al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leadge againſt this, that wee are then
<pb facs="tcp:4510:45"/> bound to confeſſe Ieſus Chriſt manifeſtly, when we are required, or conſtrained to deny him, or confeſſe him by ſome euident ſigne, as they were conſtrained, but that otherwiſe we may diſſemble the matter, eſpecially when we are not knowen nor marked therein: I knowe not what ſure foundation theſe reaſons may haue, If we be bound to confeſſe Ieſus Chriſt being in danger of life: I cannot vnderſtande how it can be lawfull for vs to deny him bee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing farre from danger.</p>
            <p>But how can it be lawfull for vs to offend <note place="margin">Sect.</note> the faythfull, and to nouriſh and eſtabliſh the faithfull in the errour of idolatrie for feare of troubling and offending the infidels; whome we cannot in better ſorte offend, then in cheri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhing and confirming them in their ſuperſtiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons and abuſes. It ſeemeth to mee that this feare of offending, is like to the charitie of ſome Anabaptiſtes, which haue beene of opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, that it was not lawfull for a Chriſtian Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrate, by iuſtice to put all thoſe to death or any other offendour, becauſe Ieſus Chriſt hath forbidden vs to reuenge euill; and for that hee hath commanded all chriſtians to ſuffer all in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iuries patiently, this is a ſtrange charitie: the ſhepheard for pittie and compaſſion he taketh on the Wolfes, he dare not hunt them from
<pb facs="tcp:4510:45"/> his flocke, but ſuffereth them to deuoure his ſheepe, and taketh more pitie of the poore wolues then of his ſheepe; and to be charita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble towardes the wolues, will be more cruell to the ſheepe then the wolues themſelues.</p>
            <p>But when all ſhall bee well examined, I <note place="margin">Sect.</note> feare much, that the diſeaſe of our fleſhe procee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth not ſo much from feare that it hath of of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence, as for feare of death: wherefore without ſeeking reaſons any further to prooue this, I aſke but the teſtimonie of conſcience, of thoſe which loue rather to cloke their infirmitie with his vayle of feare they haue to offende, then flatly to confeſſe it. I aſke then in conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence if they were out of da<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ger &amp; in ſuch liberty that they durſt boldly confeſſe that they vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand, whether for feare of offence they durſt not ſpeake of Ieſus Chriſt, and whether they would ioyne themſelues with Idolaters and keepe them companie in all their ſacrifices &amp; ceremonies? It is moſt certaine they woulde not, or els were they very euill inſtructed in the doctrine of Chriſt.</p>
            <p>I deny not, but there are ſome things, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in we might beare with the weake, and where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in <note place="margin">Sect.</note> wee ought to bee well aduiſed to take from them all iuſt cauſe of offence. If the queſtion be, whether I ſhould eate fleſhe or not eate. I
<pb facs="tcp:4510:46"/> may well vſe my libertie, if by eating I know I may alienate &amp; driue any poore ignora<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t man from the Goſpell, and in abſtayning, may draw him to the knowledge of the Goſpel, ſurely I ought to abſteyne, and to haue more regard to the edyfying of him, then to my liberty, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidering that the Apoſtle ſayth, knowledge puffeth vp, and charity doeth edyfie: for God hath not forbidden me to eate fleſhe, or to ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtaine ſome dayes, rather then others, but hath left that to my choyce on condition, that I doe all thinges to his honour and glory, and to the edyfiyng of my neighbour.</p>
            <p>But when queſtion ariſeth of any thing, <note place="margin">Sect.</note> which God hath expreſſely commanded or for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bidden, we muſt no longer there deliberate, or take counſell, or diſpute whether we muſt doe it or no? For it reſteth no longer in our power nor our iudgement: for the councell, is already taken, eyther we muſt doe it, or determine to make warre with God, and it is moſt certaine that God hath expreſſely forbidden, and with grieuous threatnings; that we ſhould not ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour nor worſhip images nor ſtrange Gods, nor yet bowe to them, nor doe any homage to them, nor to be partaker of the table of Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uels, neither by hypocriſie, nor of purpoſe: wherefore we ought to beware thereof, if that we feare to incur the diſpleaſure of indignati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
<pb facs="tcp:4510:46"/> of almightie God, and rather to chooſe the bodily death: or if we haue done otherwiſe, we muſt craue mercy and pardon of God with teares and weeping, as Peter did.</p>
            <p>I knowe well that ſome wiſe men, which take vpon them to teach others, and confeſſe <note place="margin">Sect.</note> Ieſus Chriſt priuately, but deny him openly, tell the faythfull that if they diſſemble not, they ſhould put themſelues in great danger &amp; others with them, &amp; could no longer ſerue in the church, but ſhould leaue it in great trouble. It ſeemeth that ſuche men will gouerne the Church by their wiſedome, and not leaue it to be gouerned of God by his prouidence: doe we thinke we can finde a Ieſus Chriſt whom we may ſerue without Croſſe, without perſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and without thornes? Thinke we to finde a Ieſus Chriſt ſo delicate &amp; ſoft as Ueluet? where ſhall we finde that the holy Apoſtles &amp; true diſciples of Chriſt Ieſus haue conſented to or allowed, eyther in word or deed, the idola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try &amp; abomination of the Pagans, to auoyde dangers &amp; perſecutions for feare to trouble the churches? in deed ſuch were y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Apoſtles of cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſcio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, who did greatly moleſt &amp; trouble S. <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Gal.</hi> 5. <hi>Phi.</hi> 1. 3.</note> Paule, for they endeuoured to pleaſe men, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they were enemies to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> croſſe, which they would not beare as S. Paul did.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:4510:47"/>
            <p>After the iudgement of theſe men S. Paul was a great troubler of the church, for through out all places where he was, hee was perſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted alwayes, driuen away, baniſhed, or impri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoned, becauſe of him and the doctrine that hee preached many good and faythfull men haue been in danger to thoſe, both bodies and goods, and many haue been put to death, and many townes &amp; countries moued &amp; troubled. If S. Paule would haue diſſembled, ſupported and approoued their errours, abuſes, and ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitions of Iewes and Gentiles, without ſpeaking ſo plainely, and reproouing and condemning them ſo openlye, both in worde and deede: hee might well haue auoyded all thoſe inconueniences: ſhall we then condemne him, as vndiſcrete, raſh, arrogant, and one that were mad? but if he had done otherwiſe, and if he had pleaſed men, he had not beene the ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uant of Ieſus Chriſt, he had been a traytour to <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Gal.</hi> 1.</note> his church, if for his owne bodily eaſe, and to procure the ſame to others hee had hidden the truth of God.</p>
            <p>This great Apoſtle ought in deed to haue fea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red <note place="margin">Sect.</note> as much y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the church ſhold find lack of him, if any harme ſhould come to him, as of any of vs, for there had beene farre greater loſſe, yet did not that hinder him from executing his of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice,
<pb facs="tcp:4510:47"/> according to the charge giuen him: he wil not appoint rules and limites to God, but hee followeth the rules &amp; limites y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> God hath lefte vnto him, committing him ſelf, &amp; al things els to his prouidence: for he knoweth, that all daies and all the heyres of our heade are counted, and that nothing ſhall befall vnto vs, but by the ordinance of God, who win deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine nothing but to his glory and our ſaluati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on: if he wil that we ſuffer &amp; dye for his name, our boundes, our troubles, yea our death ſhall doe better ſeruice perhaps to his Church, then our life; if he call vs out of this world, hee will ſend others into his harneſt, if men be not alto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether vnworthie thereof? If it pleaſe him that we liue and ſerue longer in his church, he is mighty and wiſe inough to keepe vs by ſuch means, as ſhal pleaſe him w<hi rend="sup">t</hi>out our dreaming &amp; inuenting means contrary to his wil: wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore as we ought not to te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pt God, nor procure harme or danger to our ſelues, ſo ought wee not for feare thereof, ſeeke ſtrange meanes, nor doe that he hath forbidden, and to agree with I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dolaters.</p>
            <p>But ſome will replie herevpon. Why then did S. Paule write that he made him ſelfe the <note place="margin">Sect.</note> ſeruant to all, and that to the Iewes he was a Iewe, and to the Gentiles a Gentile: Let vs <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mat.</hi> 16.</note>
               <pb facs="tcp:4510:48"/> take heede we iniuirie not the Apoſtle, &amp; make of him a viſer to couer our fleſhe, and to tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fourme our Satan into an angel of light, who goeth about to withdrawe vs from our office, as Peter would haue peruerted Ieſus Chriſt: that which S. Paule did, he did it to winne all to Ieſus Chriſt: &amp; that which we doe, &amp; would couer our ſelues by the example of S. Paule, ſerueth to leeſe &amp; turne away all men from Ieſus Chriſt. Think we that S. Paule did ſo accommodate himſelfe to others, that he play<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the theefe with theeues, the whoremonger with whoremongers, the drinkard with drun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kards, &amp; the idolater with idolaters? And whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he was in Epheſus, Cyprus, &amp; Athens went he with idolaters to do reuere<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce &amp; offer ſacrifices to Diana, Uenus, &amp; to Minerua, to Iupiter, &amp; to Neptune, or to any other Idol? did he not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prooue and condemne idolatrie through al pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces where he came? was not that the cauſe, why the Infidels ſtirred vp ſo great troubles &amp; per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecutions againſt him?</p>
            <p>Why then did he enter into the churche to <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Sect. Act.</hi> 21. <hi>Act.</hi> 18. 19.</note> purifie himſelfe? why made he a vowe and ſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued his heade? why did he circumciſe Timo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy? there is great difference betweene that, which S. Paul did, &amp; that we would allow by his exa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ple: for they with ceremonies were co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded
<pb facs="tcp:4510:48"/> of God, &amp; therefore was it lawfull to edyfiyng, according to the chriſtian liberty, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>til that Ieſus Chriſt was fully manifeſted, and that the Iewes were perfectly aduertiſed of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> chriſtian libertie, &amp; of the abrogating of theyr ceremonies: wherefore the diſciples did yeelde themſelues to them for a time in theſe outward thinges, and therefore haue they vſed the cere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monies, as thinges indifferent to them, which attributed no merit vnto them, but did it to draw the Iewes to a greater knowledge, &amp; fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nally to withdraw them from all ſuch obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uations.</p>
            <p>With the Gentiles in like ſort S. Paul did <note place="margin">Sect.</note> well agree, as touching their ciuile &amp; pollitike lawes, and their other indifferent kindes of dealing, which did nothing touch the conſcie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce: but we read not that he yeelded himſelfe to the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> at any time in their falſe religio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> &amp; idolatrie, for he could not do it without offe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ding god, ſeeing that y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> idolatrie was forbidden &amp; condemned of God, as y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> alſo which is now amo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gſt the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſtes: for it is inuented of men againſt the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandement of God, it hath nothing like to the iewiſh ceremonies, at that time obſerued of the Apoſtles, but it is like altogether to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> idolatry of Pagans &amp; to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> iudaiſme y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> now is amongſt y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Iewes, who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he cannot folow w<hi rend="sup">t</hi>out denying
<pb facs="tcp:4510:49"/> Ieſus Chriſt after this great manifeſtation which we haue receiued of him.</p>
            <p>And although S. Paule did beare with the <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Sect. Gal.</hi> 4. <hi>Gal.</hi> 2. <hi>Act.</hi> 16.</note> Iewes for a time, yet when he vnderſtood that ſome of them confirmed them ſelues in ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtition, and that they deſired theſe ceremonies as neceſſarie to ſaluation, he cryed out agaynſt them, and condemned them openly; and when he ſaw ſome falſe brethren come to eſpie out his libertie, he would not circumciſe Titus, as he had done Timothie, but thought y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> circu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſicion damnable, which notwithſtanding hee had vſed before, but yet as a thing indifferent: for the occaſions and circumſtances did wholy differ.</p>
            <p>Now let vs conſider howe thoſe are like to S. Paule, which will couer their Idolatry by his example, when S. Paule knoweth that y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he doth in things lawfull for a time, confirmeth the ſuperſtitions in their errour, and that they require the thing which he accounted as new<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, as neceſſary to ſaluation, he will no longer beare with them, but condemneth them ope<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ly: and when of purpoſe anie come to eſpie him, of purpoſe he reiecteth to them, without fea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring to offend eyther the falſe brethren, or the Infidels: for theſe are the offences of the Pha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſees, which are not giuen them, but they take
<pb facs="tcp:4510:49"/> them of themſelues. Contrariwiſe our hypo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crites, and diſſemblers in thinges expreſſely forbidden of God, ful of blaſphemie and ſacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, whiche the Idolaters account to be ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary for ſaluation, they will pleaſe them in it, and fayne themſelues like vnto them; and how much y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> more they are marked of them, ſo muche more they blaſpheme: they carye ſo good countenance and counterfeite the papiſt ſo well, that they paſſe all the reſt in Idolatrie, to the ende they maye bee accounted for good chriſtians, that is, for perfect Idolaters; ſuch as they are, which watch them, ſo that no man can ſuſpect or thinke otherwiſe of them.</p>
            <p>Wherefore to alleadge that in the ſacrifices <note place="margin">Sect.</note> of Idolaters, the ſupper of Ieſus Chriſt is there celebrated, it is too much to blaſpheme Chriſt Ieſus. If S. Paule haue written to thoſe which did eate fleſhe ſacrificed to Idols, without worſhipping the Idols, that they are partakers of the tables of Diuels in ſo doing: &amp; that they cannot be partakers therof, and of <note place="margin">2. <hi>Cor.</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> the table of Ieſus Chriſt both together. What would he ſay of thoſe, which wil ioyne the ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble and ſupper of Ieſus Chriſt with the table of Diuels, and with the ſacrifices wherein Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt is flatly denied and blaſphemed?
<pb facs="tcp:4510:50"/> ſuche ſacrifices are commanded or forbidden of GOD, if they bee of GOD wee ought <note place="margin">2. <hi>Cor.</hi> 6.</note> to bee ſuche as they that followe them, if they bee againſt God, howe can wee ioyne Chriſt and beliall.</p>
            <p>Some reply again vpon this and ſay, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore <note place="margin">Sect.</note> then doth S. Paule write, I will that men pray in euery place, lifting vp pure handes without wrath or diſſentio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, ſeeing he willeth y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the faythfull man pray in euery place gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally without exception, it followeth then that it is lawfull for him to pray in the temples of Idols, ſo that he pray to God, and not to the I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dols. We neede not make any other anſweare vpon this replye<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> but that whiche is alreadie made, if there were nothing but the offence that might ariſe thereof, the cauſe is ſufficient to condemne him which ſhould goe thither to make prayer, ſeeing hee hath places enough elſe for that purpoſe, without chooſing or ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counting of that place, more then another: for if hee deſire to call vpon and to honour God, he may doe that in his houſe, and enter into his Chamber according to the councel of Ieſus Chriſt, and pray to thy heauenly father in ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cret, who ſeeth him as well as if he were in an
<pb facs="tcp:4510:50"/> open place, and he wil rewarde him openly. If he deſire to pray openly to be ſeene of men, &amp; to <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mat.</hi> 6.</note> receiue prayſe therefore, as the Scribes and Phariſees, he hath receiued his rewarde alre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die with them, he witneſſeth thereby, that hee is not the true Diſciple of Ieſus Chriſt, but that he ſeeketh his owne glory, not the glorye of GOD; if hee bee deſirous and willing to gloryfie GOD before men, to ſtirre them vp by his example to doe the like, or to confeſſe him, and to make proteſtation and profeſſion of his fayth before all men: he muſt goe into the aſſemblies of the faythfull wherein God is ſanctified, not to thoſe of Idolaters where GOD is blaſphemed, or if hee will confeſſe him amongeſt Idolaters, hee muſt doe it ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in ſhewing him ſelfe to deſpiſe theyr aſſemblies, and that GOD cannot there bee honoured, but by dooing honour in the place dedicated and conſecrated to the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uell, declaring thereby, that hee thinketh that GOD maye then bee honou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red.</p>
            <p>And if there were no more, but <note place="margin">Sect.</note> that whiche Saynte Paule addeth lifting vppe pure handes, hee declareth ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſufficiently
<pb facs="tcp:4510:51"/> that men cannot do that in a place, where there is any ſparke of Idolatrie and ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perſtition. For how can hee lift vp his handes pure vnto God, who hath polluted and defiled the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> by idolatrie? for when God requireth pure handes, he ſheweth plainely that hee will haue both y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> heart &amp; the body pure &amp; cleane, without any ſpot or pollution: and we cannot deny but he is ſubiect to ſuch pollutions &amp; ſpots, whiche doth homages to the Diuell, and diſhonoureth God in that point, and killeth and murdereth <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Exod.</hi> 3.</note> the ſoule and conſcience of his brother, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>commeth guiltie of his blood, which ſhalbe re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired at his handes, the which he hath pollu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted and defiled therewith.</p>
            <p>And therefore this place cannot ſerue them, <note place="margin">Sect.</note> but to condemne them the more. For S. Paule pretendeth not by theſe woordes to induce the faythfull to frequent the aſſemblies of Idola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tries, and there to make their prayers and ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plications, but rather to withdraw them from it, giuing them to vnderſtand therby: that they ought not to take care where to pray, thought they haue no materiall temple, for they them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="6 letters">
                  <desc>••••••</desc>
               </gap> are y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> true te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ple of god: wherfore in what <note place="margin">1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 6. <hi>Ephe,</hi> 2.</note> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="4 letters">
                  <desc>••••</desc>
               </gap>e ſoeuer they be, Ieſus Chriſt dwelleth by fayth in their hearte, and ſo they are alwayes in the temple of God: wherefore God no leſſe
<pb facs="tcp:4510:51"/> heareth their prayers, then theirs which wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhipped him in the te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ple of Hieruſalem, which <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ioh.</hi> 12.</note> ought now to haue beene aboliſhed, to the ende that Ieſus Chriſt the true ſpirituall temple might onely haue place amongeſt the chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans and faithfull: and therefore after that S. Paule hath made mention of the chriſtian aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſemblies, and hath exhorted Timothie to make <note place="margin">1. <hi>Tim.</hi> 2.</note> prayers for all eſtates, and for all kinde of men; he ſayth after, that the ſame muſt be done in euery place, to the intent the faythfull may vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand, they are not tyed to the obſeruation of the Iewes, nor to their Temple, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore are they much leſſe to the temple of Ido<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laters.</p>
            <p>There is yet another place which they will haue to ſerue their turne, becauſe S. Paule <note place="margin">Sect.</note> ſaith. If any brother haue an infidel to his wife and ſhe conſent to dwell with him: Let him not forſake her. And the woman that hath an <note place="margin">1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> Infidel to her huſband, &amp; he be content to dwel with her: Let her not forſake him, for the vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>belieuing huſba<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d is ſanctified by the belieuing wife, and the vnbelieuing wife is ſanctified by the belieuing huſband, otherwiſe your childre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> were polluted &amp; vncleane, but now are they ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly. They wil conclude by this, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> if it be lawfull for the faythful to dwel with his infidel wife, &amp;
<pb facs="tcp:4510:52"/> to vſe her, and to be ſerued of her, that by the ſame reaſon, they maye alſo vſe the ceremo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies and manners of doing, which are amongſt the ſuperſtitious and Idolaters. For if they be polluted and defiled to the Infidels, yet are they not ſo to them, but are cleane and holye, for to the cleane, are all things cleane, but to the vncleane and Infidelles, all thinges are <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Tit.</hi> 1 <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> vncleane. They ſaye further, that euen as the Apoſtle will that the partie faythfull for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſake not the Infidell, if ſhee conſent to dwell with him, becauſe the huſbande or the wife beeing faythfull knowe not whether they can winne the partie vnfaythfull, ſo they knowe not whether GOD by theyr meane will winne and call backe the poore blinde and ignorant.</p>
            <p>I am greatly aſhamed when I ſee the <note place="margin">Sect.</note> Chriſtians dallye in this ſorte with the word of GOD, and drawe it ſo violently by the hayre, to make it ſerue for their blaſphemie: what agreement is there betweene the par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie infidell and the Idoles, If Saint Paule had ſayde that of a Whoore or Whooremon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, and had allowed that the faythfull man might dwell with an Harlot, and vſe her in whooredome, although ſhe were an Infidell;
<pb facs="tcp:4510:52"/> if ſhee would cary with him, or a whooremon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger with a Chriſtian woman, their argument and compariſon had ſome coulor, but the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle ſpeaketh in this place of ſuch as are ioyned by lawfull marriage, for marriage is of ſuch authoritie, and ſo faſt and indiſſoluble, that God will not that it ſhould be broken or violated, nor that y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> huſband or y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> wife ſeparate the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues one from another, although one of them ſhould ſtricke obſtinately in infidelitie, if that the par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie vnfaythfull woulde not hinder the faythful to doe his duetie to God: for if the huſbande would not ſuffer his wife with him, except ſhe would forſake Ieſus Chriſt, but that he would driue her away and forſake her, if ſhe would not ſo doe to conſent to his infidelitie &amp; idolatry: in ſuch a caſe S. Paule wil not y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> the wife be ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iect to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> huſband, or y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> huſband tied to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> wife, he alloweth in ſuch a caſe, that the faythfull for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſake rather the infidell, then God, and that he ſuffer her to depart from him, rather then to ſuffer himſelfe ſeparated from Ieſus Chriſt. <note place="margin">1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 7.</note> For in ſuch caſes it is fitte to practiſe y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> which Chriſt Ieſus hath ſaid. He that leaueth not fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther and mother, brother, ſiſter, wife, and chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, goodes, poſſeſſions, for my ſake, he is not worthy of me.</p>
            <p>But if the infidell ſuffer the faythfull <note place="margin">Sect.</note>
               <pb facs="tcp:4510:53"/> to liue in his libertie and religion, then the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Apoſtle, will that he beare with the Infidell and not to reiect her nor forſake her therefore: and that for two cauſes. Firſt to ſhew what ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour we owe vnto the holy ordinances of God, and in what reputation we ought to haue the holy marriage. Secondly, becauſe there is yet ſome hope of winning the infidell, for al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though the wife of the chriſtian be yet a Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſt, or Infidel, and Idolater, yet if in other thinges ſhee doe the office of an obedient wife towardes her huſband, if ſhe bee a good huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wife and doe gouerne his family well, and ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dereth vnto him the duetie and reuerence ſhee oweth vnto him, he ought to keepe her: ſith God hath giuen her vnto him, and ioyned her with him? For although ſhe be an Infidel, yet her infidelitie cannot hurt her faythfull huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band, if he be not partaker thereof, his faith can not be made voyde by the infidelitie and Ido<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latry of his wife, whileſt he perſeuereth therin, and alloweth not the infidelitie and Idolatry of his wife, but reprooueth her, and endeuou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth to correct her as much as he can: yet the Apoſtle will not that the faythful partie ſhould communicate with the infidelitie and Idola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trie of the other in hope to winne her, for it were a ſle<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>der gain to looſe two, in ſteed of win<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning
<pb facs="tcp:4510:53"/> one, but wil that the faithfull partie keepe it ſelfe pure and cleane, and ſeparate it ſelfe ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther then to conſent to that.</p>
            <p>And therefore this place is flat contrary vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to <note place="margin">Sect.</note> them that alleadge it for their defence. for if Saint Paule, doeth permit the faithfull partie to chooſe rather to bee ſeparated, then to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent to the infidelitie and idolatrie of the other, which is, one body, one fleſh and blood with her: howe can he allowe that wee ſhoulde conſente to idolatrie, to dwel with thoſe which haue not the thirde part of ſuch coniunction with vs, as the huſbande and the wife haue together? If God, who hath commanded that the man ſhould leaue father &amp; mother, &amp; cleaue &amp; ioyne to his wife, will y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> man forſake her rather, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to deny his worde, how can he like we ſhoulde commit ſuch Sacrileges, to keepe our ſelues ſtill a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongeſt thoſe, which are nothing in compari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon to vs, or touch vs very little; for what ſigni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fieth theſe words els: If the infidel go his way <note place="margin">1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 7.</note> and depart, let him go: for the brother or y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſiſter are not ſubiect in ſuche matters? What els doth this meane, but that if the infidell doe her duetie in the reſt, and if there bee no diſagree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment but for religion, that there can be no ſepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration for that, for els it were doubtful. For many huſbandes vnder colour of the Goſpel,
<pb facs="tcp:4510:54"/> woulde forſake their wiues, and many wiues their huſbandes, and one knoweth not whether the partie faithfull can bring the other to the knowledge of the trueth, wherein there is yet more hope that a man may profite with a Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſt, then with a Paga<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, as they were in the time of Saint Paule. For in the action of religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on there is more agreement betweene the faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full and the papiſts, then there was at y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> time be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> faithfull &amp; the Pagans: but if the par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie Infidell be ſo peruerſe, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> it is not poſſible to dwell with it without forſaking Ieſus Chriſt, the bond wherewith we are tyed to it, ought to be ſtronger.</p>
            <p>Although then that the partie Infidell diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleaſe <note place="margin">Sect.</note> God, becauſe of her infidelitie, yet doeth it not followe thereby, that I may not vſe it in that for which God hath giuen it vnto me, &amp; ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to his order that hee hath ſet among men as well as with any other creature of god, as with the Magiſtrate, the Prince, and the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther being infidels: for if God haue giuen mee a Magiſtrate, or a Prince that is an Infidell, I may vſe him as touching his office without of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence to God, for although hee bee an Infidell and diſpleaſeth God therein, yet his office cea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth not to bee of God: and therefore I may
<pb facs="tcp:4510:54"/> vſe him to the honour of God, in all things that concerne the office of a true Magiſtrate, ſo that I conſent not, or agree to his Idolatrie. For although that he through his infidelitie cannot pleaſe God in his own perſon, yet to me which vſe him according to the ordinance of God, he is holy. In this maner Saint Paul did vſe the Burgeſſes of Rome, and did appeale before the Emperour, and vſed the Pagan Magiſtrates to defend his cauſe in that they were Miniſters of God: but he did neuer therefore allowe the Idolatrie of Rome, nor conſented to any thing that was againſt God, ſo the faithfull man may vſe his vnfaithfull wife: if he be to marry, hee doth euill, if he take her to wife, whom hee kno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>weth to be an infidel, but if he haue her alredie, before hee knowe the trueth, and ſhee will not receiue the trueth with him, he may vſe her not withſtanding as his wife, for although ſhee bee euill and polluted before God as touching her ſelfe, yet is ſhe ſanctified to the vſe of the faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iob.</hi> 1.</note> for ſeeing all belongeth to God, the faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful man may vſe all y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> belongeth to God; as his owne, becauſe hee is the childe of God, and for <note place="margin">1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 13.</note> that all the treaſures of God belongeth vnto him, for all is ours.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:4510:55"/>
            <p>But the Infidell cannot vſe any thing what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer <note place="margin">Sect.</note> it is without ſinning &amp; offending God, there is nothing ſo cleane, which hee polluteth not: for ſeeing hee is defiled, and is not purified nor cleanſed by faith in Ieſus Chriſte; All things are vncleane to him, and he polluteth all thinges: ſeeing that by faith, hee is not the childe of God, hee cannot vſe the goods and creatures of God, but as a theefe, vſurping that which nothing apperteineth to him: for as all thinges are cleane to the cleane, ſo on the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary, euery thing is vncleane to them that are defiled and Infidels, or that haue not a pure conſcience, but are ſeparated from all good workes. And therefore although the wife bee faithfull, if the huſband be an Infidell, yet the wife, although in her ſelfe ſhee bee holy &amp; ſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctified vnto God, yet ſhee is prophane and pol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luted to the huſbande, as touching his vſe, for ſeeing hee is none of the children of God, hee is not worthy to haue his creatures ſerue him. Wherefore hee doeth iniurie both to the Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor, and creature, when hee maketh her to ſerue him, &amp; he will not ſerue the Creator, who hath <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> her to his vſe, and to whome that crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture ſerueth: contrariwiſe, if the wife bee faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, although the huſband bee an Infidell, yet the huſbande who in himſelfe is polluted and
<pb facs="tcp:4510:55"/> dedicated to the Deuill; yet is he notwithſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding holy vnto her, and ſanctified as to her vſe, that is, ſhe may vſe him as her huſbande in that which concerneth the eſtate and office of mari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>age without offe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce to God. The vnfaithful huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band is aſ well ſanctified vnto her, as the breade <note place="margin">1. <hi>Tim.</hi> 4.</note> which ſhe eateth, and as other thinges which ſhe vſeth with giuing of thankes.</p>
            <p>Alſo the father that is an infidell is ſanctifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed <note place="margin">Sect.</note> to the faithfull child<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>, and the children of the faithfull and vnfaithfull are holy, becauſe of the faithfull, and though the children ſhoulde be in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidels, yet the party faithfull might vſe them in that which is due to the childe, by the father and mother, without offence to God, as well as we may vſe a horſe or an aſſe, according to their nature, although they be not men, nor haue not fayth: for we ſerue our ſelues with them, as the good creatures of God, in that wherevnto they are created.</p>
            <p>But wee muſt alwayes beware, that we a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buſe not the creatures, and that we peruert not <note place="margin">Sect.</note> the vſe of them, for although it be lawful for me to vſe my wife, if ſhee be an infidel, as touching the ſtate of marriage, yet is it not lawfull for me to vſe an other woman in whoredome, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though ſhee be a Chriſtian: for whoredome is <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Exod.</hi> 20. <hi>Math.</hi> 7.</note> not ordeined of God, as holy matrimonie is, but
<pb facs="tcp:4510:56"/> forbidden and condemned, and therefore as re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion cannot ſeparate marriage, if marriage hinder not, nor take away the religion, ſo reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion cannot make whoredome good, but whore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome doth breake and violate the religion.</p>
            <p>Wee ought to thinke euen ſo of idolatrie: <note place="margin">Sect.</note> for although it be lawful for me, to vſe the ſame corne and bread for my nouriſhment, which ido<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laters vſe for theirs, and alſo of the ſame wood that they warme them ſelues with, to nouriſhe and warme me as they doe, yet is it not lawfull for mee to vſe breade and wine, that they haue conſecrated in the table of deuils, and of which they haue made an Idol: nor likewiſe of their wood in that maner that they vſe it to idolatrie, for they put it to an other vſe, then it was ordei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned of God, &amp; they peruert the order of his cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>atures, &amp; therefore they abuſe them; And ſo is it no longer vſe, but abuſe, ſinne, and a deteſtable fault: for the idole can in no ſort be ſanctified to God, ſeeing thereby he is diſhonoured; It can pleaſe him no more, then the harlot which alto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether reſiſteth his will.</p>
            <p>And therfore thoſe which make ſuch allega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, may well conſider what violence they do <note place="margin">Sect.</note> vnto the ſcriptures, &amp; whether they ſpeake well to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> purpoſe, to compare the idols conſecrated to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> diuel, to the holy marriage, &amp; to the lawfull
<pb facs="tcp:4510:56"/> vſe of the good creature of God: for no man can vſe the idolles to good in that maner that they are ordered amongſt the idolaters. Theſe men that make ſuch compariſons, put me in mind of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> whoremongers, which ſay, when any reproo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of whoredom, why then did God make women but to ſerue mans turne? It is true that God hath made woman to ſerue man to his glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, but he hath not created her that man ſhoulde abuſe her, and ſhould diſhonour and blaſpheme God by her: and therefore he hath limitted vnto him, the vſe of her, &amp; how he ought to ſerue him ſelfe by her, &amp; wherin money is created of God, &amp; likewiſe corne &amp; wine, yet is there a meane in vſing of it: there is in this an order amongſt men, ſo that I vſe of mine owne authoritie mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney, which God hath put into the hands of ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, &amp; if I take it for my ſelfe, without his will and conſent, and by other meanes the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> God hath appoynted, I am a thiefe. Alſo if I vſe a wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man as my wife out of marriage, I abuſe y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ature of God, &amp; am a whoremonger, if it be ſo of the good creatures of God, what ought it to be of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ceremonies, ſuperſtitions, &amp; inuented idols of the diuell, agaynſt the commaundement of God? howe can they be holy to me? howe can I pleaſe God in corrupting his creatures and peruerting his orders?</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:4510:57"/>
            <p>I am not ignoraunt of the other replicati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons <note place="margin">Sect.</note> and obiections that men haue accuſtomed to make, to peruert all the argumentes and rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons heretofore alleadged, to confirme our opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion. It ſeemeth to them whiche are of the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary opinion, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> they haue confuted al y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſtrong<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt arguments, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> we can alleadge touching this matter, and that they haue wholly wonne the fielde, in that they make them ſelues beleeue there is great difference betweene them and theſe examples, which wee vſe to beate downe their opinion: they further alwayes abuſe them ſelues, that it ſeemeth to them, that the ſacrifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of Idolaters, with whome they are conuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſant, howe impure ſo euer they bee, yet are not offered, but to the honor of the true God (whom they confeſſe with vs) not to the honour of ſtrange goddes: And therefore it ſeemeth to them, there is great difference betweene theſe ſacrifices, and thoſe of the pagans. <note place="margin">Sect.</note>
            </p>
            <p>They are very ignoraunt, if they thinke there was neuer people nor nation, whiche thought to worſhip and honour any other then the true God, the Scripture condemneth not ſimply the pagans and idolaters for worſhip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping any thing but God, and hauing ſerued the diuell in ſteede of him, but becauſe that going about to ſerue God after their owne fancie, and not according to his worde, in ſteede of ſeruing
<pb facs="tcp:4510:57"/> God, they haue ſerued the diuell goddes that they haue forged of their owne braine, their in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent was good to haue ſerued the true God, but becauſe it was not directed according to his worde, and they imagined God after their own fancie, and meaſured him after their affec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; the holy ghoſt condemneth them, and cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth them a people without a God, and ſayeth their gods are diuels.</p>
            <p>What difference then is there betweene the <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Sect. Ephe.</hi> 2. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 95.</note> Iſraelites and the Pagans? why is that god whom the Iſraelites ſerue, taken for the true God, and thoſe of the Gentiles, for Idols, Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uels, and falſe gods? there is no other reaſon, but that becauſe the Iſraelites ſerue God ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to his lawe, and receiue him as he pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenteth and manifeſteth himſelf to them, and do not diſguiſe him as they liſt, neither put they other garmentes on him then hee hath taken to himſelfe: and therefore hee is to them the true God, but becauſe the Pagans and Idolaters woulde colour and diſguiſe him by their inuen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, ceremonies, and ſuperſtitions after their owne fancie, and woulde haue that to be good to him, which ſeemed good to them, and woulde ſubiect him to their lawes, where they ought to be ſubiect to his, they haue wholie loſt him.</p>
            <p>Seeing then that they ſeeke God by other <note place="margin">Sect.</note>
               <pb facs="tcp:4510:58"/> meanes, then thoſe by which he will be knowne and honoured, they cannot find him: but in ſteed of God, who hath made them, they find out gods that they themſelues haue made, by the imagi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation of their owne vnderſtanding, for God cannot be other then he is: wherefore if we at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tribute that vnto him, which apperteyneth not to him, or take that from him, which appertay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth to him, he ceaſeth not in his eſſence &amp; ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ieſtie to be alwayes God, but vnto vs, he is no more God, but is changed to vs into the idole whiche our affections hath forged vnto vs, but the idole which we haue faigned to our ſelues, cannot be God: wherefore we haue already al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tered him into a diuell, which ought to bee God vnto vs, ſeeyng we would order him according to our pleaſure.</p>
            <p>Let vs now co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſider, if there be any other diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence <note place="margin">Sect.</note> betweene thoſe which followe the trueth of the Goſpel, and the others which will ſerue God after mens traditions, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> this, wherof we ſpeake: what is there that letteth vs fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> being at agreement with the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, but this difference? for we confeſſe al one God, one Ieſus Chriſt, one Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpel, and like articles of the fayth, and yet is there as great difference betweene the one and the other, as betweene heauen and earth: for ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing God is ſerued in vaine by the doctrines and
<pb facs="tcp:4510:58"/> commaundementes of men, it followeth neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſarily, <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Eſai.</hi> 29. <hi>Mat.</hi> 15.</note> that thoſe whiche ſerue him otherwiſe then hee hath commaunded, ſerue him not: it muſt needes be then, that they ſerue a God, who is not God in deede, but onely in imagination, for although they confeſſe God with the mouth, yet they denie him in woorkes. Thoſe then <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Tit.</hi> 1.</note> which are acquainted with them, and do as they do, wherein doe they differ from them, but that ſome are more ignorant then others? and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore leſſe to bee excuſed: for it is good reaſon, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the ſeruant which knoweth his maſters wil and doth it not, ſhould be more grieuouſly puniſhed, then he that neither knoweth it, nor doeth it.</p>
            <p>The others, becauſe they haue not the true <note place="margin">Sect.</note> knowledge of God, doe dedicate their bodies &amp; ſoules to their half gods: Thou y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> haſt y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of God, &amp; knoweſt how he wil be ſerued, thou wilt part ſtakes with him, thou wilt make the parts, &amp; diſtribute the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> as thou liſt: thou ſaieſt thou giueſt y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> heart &amp; y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſoule to God: &amp; who ſhal haue the body, the diuel? God hath no parting with the diuel, he will haue the body &amp; the ſoule whollie, or els he wil haue neither, if he had not promiſed life eternal, but to the ſoule, &amp; that hee woulde onely glorifie it, and leaue the body in corruption and damnation, there were ſome more colour to ſerue God with y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> heart &amp; ſoule,
<pb facs="tcp:4510:59"/> and his aduerſarie with the body, but ſeeyng he will glorifie both the one and the other, and that he hath ſanctified them to dwel in them, and to tranſforme them to his image: howe is it <note place="margin">1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 13. 2. <hi>Cor.</hi> 3. <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.</note> poſſible that the ſoule ſhoulde carrie the marke and image of God, and the body the image of the diuell? howe is it poſſible, that a man who is but one ſhoulde be deuided into two, that hee may well ſerue two maſters, without offending the one or the other? Ieſus Chriſt hath ſaide it is impoſſible to ſerue well two maſters. If it be not poſſible to ſerue God and riches, howe can <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mat.</hi> 6.</note> we ſerue God and Idols, and the diuel in them?</p>
            <p>But leaſt perhappes it ſeeme that theſe <note place="margin">Sect.</note> reaſons be not ſufficient, and that there is no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing like between the papiſts and the pagans: let vs take a more euident exa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ple. What other difference was there betwixt Iuda and Iſrael, after y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> Ieroboam had made the golden calues, but that whiche is betweene vs and our aduer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaries, all of them did boaſt to bee the people of God, the ſonnes of Abraham, and to haue recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued the lawe of the Lord by Moſes: The Iſrae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lites did knowe their calues of gold, and their images of Baal were not goddes, but they kept them for a remembrance of GOD, and to honour him by them: they had no other opinion then the Chriſtians haue of theyrs,
<pb facs="tcp:4510:59"/> they did not vnderſtande, that they had forſaken God to ſerue an other. The prophetes haue not yet refuſed to accuſe them to haue forſaken God, to ſerue ſtrange Gods, and to threaten them with his iudgement. Did Helias alowe the doing of thoſe which ſerued Baal, in time of the greate perſecution which Ieſabel put in practiſe againſt the faithfull? And the ſeuen thouſand, which God hath reſerued to himſelf, are they only prayſed in that they did not honor Baal with the heart? are they not expreſly prai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed in that he bowed not the knee to him, and did him no homage, honour, nor reuerence, and that they kept their bodies without being pol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luted and defiled amongſt others with the ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crilidges and abhominations of Baal?</p>
            <p>Wee haue no reaſons which the Idolaters in this time cannot bring for their defence, they <note place="margin">Sect.</note> coulde alleadge that the people, which ſerued Baal, were not Pagans, but their owne bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren brought vp one religion, on lawe, and one faith with them: wee haue no colour for to ſet out our Images and our gods, whether they be of golde, ſiluer, wood, ſtones, bread or meate, which they had not to colour Baal, and the <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Io.</hi> 3.</note> golden Calues, and eſpecially the braſen Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent. For that Image had much more rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon and greater ſhewe then all ours, and ſo
<pb facs="tcp:4510:60"/> and his aduerſarie with the body, but ſeeyng he will glorifie both the one and the other, and that he hath ſanctified them to dwel in them, and to tranſforme them to his image: howe is it <note place="margin">1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 13. 2. <hi>Cor.</hi> 3. <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.</note> poſſible that the ſoule ſhoulde carrie the marke and image of God, and the body the image of the diuell? howe is it poſſible, that a man who is but one ſhoulde be deuided into two, that hee may well ſerue two maſters, without offending the one or the other? Ieſus Chriſt hath ſaide it is impoſſible to ſerue well two maſters. If it be not poſſible to ſerue God and riches, howe can <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mat.</hi> 6.</note> we ſerue God and Idols, and the diuel in them?</p>
            <p>But leaſt perhappes it ſeeme that theſe <note place="margin">Sect.</note> reaſons be not ſufficient, and that there is no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing like between the papiſts and the pagans: let vs take a more euident exa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ple. What other difference was there betwixt Iuda and Iſrael, after y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> Ieroboam had made the golden calues, but that whiche is betweene vs and our aduer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaries, all of them did boaſt to bee the people of God, the ſonnes of Abraham, and to haue recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued the lawe of the Lord by Moſes: The Iſrae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lites did knowe their calues of gold, and their images of Baal were not goddes, but they kept them for a remembrance of GOD, and to honour him by them: they had no other opinion then the Chriſtians haue of theyrs,
<pb facs="tcp:4510:60"/> they did not vnderſtande, that they had forſaken God to ſerue an other. The prophetes haue not yet refuſed to accuſe them to haue forſaken God, to ſerue ſtrange Gods, and to threaten them with his iudgement. Did Helias alowe the doing of thoſe which ſerued Baal, in time of the greate perſecution which Ieſabel put in practiſe againſt the faithfull? And the ſeuen thouſand, which God hath reſerued to himſelf, are they only prayſed in that they did not honor Baal with the heart? are they not expreſly prai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed in that he bowed not the knee to him, and did him no homage, honour, nor reuerence, and that they kept their bodies without being pol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luted and defiled amongſt others with the ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crilidges and abhominations of Baal?</p>
            <p>Wee haue no reaſons which the Idolaters <note place="margin">Sect.</note> in this time cannot bring for their defence, they coulde alleadge that the people, which ſerued Baal, were not Pagans, but their owne bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren brought vp one religion, on lawe, and one faith with them: wee haue no colour for to ſet out our Images and our gods, whether they be of golde, ſiluer, wood, ſtones, bread or meate, which they had not to colour Baal, and the <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Io.</hi> 3.</note> golden Calues, and eſpecially the braſen Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent. For that Image had much more rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon and greater ſhewe then all ours, and ſo
<pb facs="tcp:4510:61"/> much more dangerous was it: if we may ſpeak of the perſecutio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, and of the feare of Tyrants, I doubt not, but it was cruell, and more cruell in Helias time then in ours. Heliah ſaith not without cauſe, they haue killed thy Prophetes <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. <hi>Reg.</hi> 19.</note> and there is none left, but I, whome they ſeeke to the death.</p>
            <p>But I maruaile at thoſe, which will make the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues a buckler of Abdas, Achas his ſtew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>arde, <note place="margin">Sect.</note> ſaying, he was one of the faithfull fearing God, and yet was ſeruant to Achab and that peruerſe Ieſabell: Wherefore it is not like that hee can tarie in their ſeruice without ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing of Baal, as they did at the leaſt in outward ſhewe: this reaſon is but a vaine thought and an imagination and preſumption of mans vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding: for there is not one worde in all the hiſtorie, no not one ſillable, by which they can prooue this Imagination; but rather altoge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the contrarie: and woulde to GOD that thoſe which will arme them ſelues with this example, had as good a minde and af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection to hide the poore perſecuted, and to ſuccoure them in their neceſſitie, as Abdias had, and ſhewed in deede to the prophets and faithfull of his time: and though Abdias had done that which they preſume and imagine, it followeth not therefore that he was allowed of
<pb facs="tcp:4510:61"/> God, no more then other ſinnes of the ſaints.ſaints. <note place="margin">Sect.</note>
            </p>
            <p>But beholde, yet an other replie, which ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth not apparant, if it be ſo dangerous a thing <note place="margin">4. <hi>Reg.</hi> 5.</note> &amp; ſo contrary to the will of God to be partaker of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ceremonies &amp; ſacrifices of the papiſts, why did Elizeus anſwere Naaman the Aſſyrian, go thy way in peace? After that Naaman ſaid vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to him, when my Lord ſhall enter into the tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of Remmon to worſhip, &amp; ſhall leaue vpon my hand, &amp; on my ſhoulder, pray the Lord that he wil pardo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> me thy ſeruant for this thing, if I worſhip in the temple of Remmo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, when I ſhall worſhip in the ſame place: Elizeus maketh no difficultie to ſuffer him ſo to do, he condemmeth it not, as a damnable thing that he ſhould enter into the temples of idols w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the Pagans, &amp; that he ſhould be preſent at their ſacrifice, ſo that he worſhip God in his heart, why ſhal wee then be rather forbidden, to co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>municate in like ſort w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> thoſe y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> are Chriſtians as we are, then Naaman w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the paga<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, who were in deed enemies to god?</p>
            <p>This exa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ple ſhall ſerue vs no more then y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> of S. Paul: it might ſerue your turn if you were like to Naaman, &amp; if to doe ſeruice vnto any, to whom you were bound in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſight of God, you ſhould go w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ſort, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> Naaman kept com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> his lord. For he went not thither to co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit idolatry, as he did, or to allow his idolatry,
<pb facs="tcp:4510:62"/> but to ſerue him as a ſeruant, in his neceſſities? Wherefore we muſt vnderſtand, that, to wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, is often taken in ſcripture to bow, and do reuerence by outwarde ſignes and geſtures, as wee doe to kinges and Princes, the Idolaters to their Idols, and the faithfull alſo to God, when as by outwarde geſtures and ſignes they will declare the humilitie of their heart, and the reuerence they beare to God: but Naaman re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quireth not to bee ſuffered to kneele and doe re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerence before the God Remmon: and to wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip notwithſtanding the true God in his heart, to declare by outwarde ſignes, that hee beareth reuerence to the God Remmon, to pleaſe the king as they do, which by outward geſtures do worſhip the hoſt and Images, and yet ſay their heart is not there, but that by it they worſhippe Ieſus Chriſt in heauen, and the father in ſpirite and truth.</p>
            <p>Naaman ſpeaketh not of that adoration as <note place="margin">Sect.</note> touching himſelfe; but only of the reuerence he ought to ſhewe in ſeruing the king, when hee woulde kneele or bow downe before Remmon. For ſeeing hee muſt bee in the ſeruice of his Prince, and ſtay him when he leaned vpon him, the king coulde not bowe, but that Naa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man alſo was enclined to bowe that the king might leaue vpon him: But Naaman did it not
<pb facs="tcp:4510:62" rendition="simple:additions"/> for Remmon as the king did, nor to make the king beleeue that he honoured Remmon, as he did, fearing to diſpleaſe him, but hee did it not only to ſerue his Prince according to his due<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, for before hee agreed to that hee promiſed, and witneſſed openly that hee would doe no ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifice to the ſtrange gods, but to the liuing God: ſeeing that hee promiſed ſo, wee muſt not doubt but that hee kept his promiſe: and it is moſt certaine, that in the eſtate &amp; dignitie wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in hee was, hee coulde not tarry any long tyme without ſacrificing to the Idols as others did: but it would haue been perceiued; but he would that euery one ſhould know &amp; vnderſtande, that he had in his heart: there is no doubt but that for this cauſe hee demanded of Elizeus, two mules charged with the earth of Iſrael, to take with him into the land of Syria, to beare wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes and make publike confeſſion that he belee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued not, nor worſhipped any other then God of Iſrael, &amp; that he had his diuine ſeruice aparte, &amp; ſeparated from that of the other Syrians, who were Idolaters.</p>
            <p>And although he did all things, &amp; that he had <note place="margin">Sect.</note> far better cauſe then thoſe which woulde de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend their Idolatrie by his example, yet doeth he not ſo much iuſtifie his works, as they doe, but he requireth the Prophete, to the ende hee
<pb facs="tcp:4510:63"/> ſhould pray to God for him, that he woulde not impute that as a ſinne to him: wherein he ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth well that there was ſome infirmitie in him, and that he feareth there ſhould bee ſome faulte in that worke, which the Prophet rather bea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth with all, then alloweth, yea although that before hee had done other thinges enough to confeſſe his faith before men: And if wee conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der well the wordes of Naaman, hee confeſſeth very manifeſtly that he thinketh there is ſinne, in y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he ſaith, he muſt doe, ſeeing he willeth the Prophet to pray for him, that it may not be im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puted to him, for if there be no fault, there is no neede of prayer nor pardon, and Elizeus ſaieth not the contrarie to him, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> it is not ſinne at all, but he wil not preſſe him ouermuch in the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion he made of the name of God: &amp; therfore he letteth him go, &amp; giueth him to vnderſtand, he will do y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> which Naaman requireth of him: that is, that he will pray for him, &amp; biddeth him fare well: wherefore although it were ſo, that Elizeus had borne with ſome great faulte in Naaman, who was yet a nouice, and newely come to the religion, &amp; was come from amo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gſt the Pagans, it followeth not therefore that wee which are Chriſtians, and haue receiued a grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter knowledge of truth confirmed by the death
<pb facs="tcp:4510:63"/> of Ieſus Chriſt, and ſo many martyrs, ought to draw this particular example to a general con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequent, &amp; to ſet it againſt ſo many places of ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſcripture: which forbid all Idolatrie and all ſhew of denying Ieſus Chriſte.</p>
            <p>If wee teſtifie publikelie our faith, and if we confeſſe we attribute nothing to the Idols, but <note place="margin">Sect.</note> that we goe to the aſſemblies of Idolaters to ſerue our father or ſome other, to whom we are bounde, not in Idolatrie, but in that which may concerne our office: the example of Naaman might giue vs ſome further colour for our for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer confeſſion, and the publike witneſſing of our faith, woulde glorifie God, and condemne the Idolaters, and ſtrengthen the faithfull, and woulde take away all cauſe of offending the good, and woulde leaue no matter to the Ido<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laters wherin to glorifie: but the cauſe why we goe, it is to doe farre contrary, it is to couer vs, and not to vncouer vs.</p>
            <p>Yet notwithſtanding, if wee ſhoulde doe as <note place="margin">Sect.</note> Naaman did, yet ought we no more to iuſtifie our ſelues, then he; but wee ought to aſke par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>do<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of God for it, as he did. And if Naama<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> were afraid to offend God by y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> act, although he had a goodly cloke to excuſe himſelfe, I aſhamed of thoſe w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> are quite co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>trary to him, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> they dare ſo
<pb facs="tcp:4510:64"/> aſſuredly defend their worke as if there were no ſinne in it. And to make their matter better, after they had red y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> which was written againſt their opinion, &amp; ſeene themſelues bereft of that weapon, which they tooke from the example of Naaman to defend their cauſe, they ſought an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other ſtarting hole, wherein there is ſlender foundation: they haue imagined, that when Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aman made y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> confeſſion to Elizeus, which was ſpoke<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of before, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> it is very like he was alone, &amp; that he ſaid it not before al the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pany which was w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> him, they proue their imaginatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> by this, that it is the cuſtome of great Lordes to ſpeake in a Maieſtie of their affaires, &amp; in the abſence of their ſeruants, rather then in their preſence. Wherefore they cauſe the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to depart, &amp; for bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter confirmation hereof, they alleadge y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> when Geazi, ran after Naaman, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> Naaman deſce<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded out of his chariot, &amp; that hee came before him. Wherefore they conclude, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he ſpake to him a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>part, &amp; in abſence of his ſeruants, and that hee might well do as much to Elizeus, when hee vſed that talke with him, wherof the holy ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture maketh mention.</p>
            <p>This is the ſophiſtrie, whereby ſome wil now <note place="margin">Sect.</note> adayes make this exa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ple of force to helpe an e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uill cauſe: but I know not to what ende it may ſerue them, but to ſhew that thoſe which are ſo ſeene in ſpeculation to imagine theſe ſtarting
<pb facs="tcp:4510:64"/> holes, know wel what they haue to doe, &amp; that it ſeemeth they are deſirous to finde ſome cloke in ſcriptures, to couer their matter, &amp; that they would gladly make the ſpirite of God, which ſpeaketh in his holy ſcriptures, to thinke that he would ſpeake &amp; vnderſtande things as they would haue it: For as for the firſt, all their rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon is grounded but vpon imagination, which it is as eaſie to diſproue as to allowe: but of thinges of ſo great importance, wee muſt not iudge vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> preſumptio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s &amp; imaginatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s. More<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouer the ſcripture doth manifeſtly witnes, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he promiſed &amp; co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>feſſed he would ſerue none other God, but y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Lord, &amp; woulde declare it by ſacrifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, and by outward confeſſion, &amp; publike teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monie, &amp; to giue this teſtimony, he deſired theſe two mules charged w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the earth of Iſrael, as his wordes do manifeſtly witnes. For to what purpoſe ſhould y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> earth ſerue him, more then the earth of Syria, but to this end? then wee haue no cauſe to doubt, but that y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> matter is eaſie, as he hath purpoſed &amp; demanded it: For y<hi rend="sup">t</hi>, which the prophet anſwered him after y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> maner which the Hebrwes vſe in their ſalutations, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> they bid a man farewell, ſaying to him, goe in peace, ought not y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> only to be reſerued to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> laſt ſpeech, that Naama<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vſed touching his worſhipping in the Temple of Remmon, but to all his former
<pb facs="tcp:4510:65"/> woordes wherein the Prophete conſenteth to him? The matter then is plaine, that his confeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion was not ſecrete, but publike, and therefore his example ſerueth to no ende for them, which content them ſelues to haue confeſſed Ieſus Chriſte in ſecrete before a fewe, and blaſpheme him publikely.</p>
            <p>It is eaſie to vnderſtande all theſe thinges: <note place="margin">Sect.</note> but we ſeeke theſe cloking &amp; ſtarting holes, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe we wil not be vnfurniſhed. And what is y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> cauſe, if we ſhould diſcouer our ſelues, we ſhold yeeld our ſelues all vnto death, and ſhoulde bee murtherers of our ſelues? But thoſe which are out of this danger may babble at their eaſe: our life coſteth them little, I know ſome vſe ſuche ſpeech, but yet their life is dearer to vs, then they thinke for: we are no leſſe afraide to put them in danger then themſelues: for wee are not out of pryſon without being mindefull of them, &amp; feeling y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> afflictions of our brethren as if we were there our ſelues: and therefore it is more ſafe to followe the iudgementes of thoſe which are out of danger, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> thoſe which are in it, it is very hard y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the ſicke man ſhoulde be a good Phiſitio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to himſelfe: but he hath need of another, for it is doubtfull, hee would rather make the medicine ſerue his affections, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> rule his affections by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> art of Phiſicke, for ſickneſſe deſireth to entertaine it ſelfe, &amp; willeth alwaies
<pb facs="tcp:4510:65"/> that is contrarie vnto it: the ſicke man alſo be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeueth rather the phiſitions which accord vnto his will, then they that gaine ſay it: It is very hard alſo that a man ſhould bee a good iudge of his owne cauſe, for hardly could he auoide, but his affections woulde cary him away, &amp; hinder him fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſeeing the right &amp; giuing good iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; wherefore it is requiſite to ſeeke iudges which be not ouermuch affectioned to the mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, &amp; do not iudge at randon according to their fancie, but bee of good co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſcience with out loo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king to the affection of any but to God only, &amp; to right and equitie.</p>
            <p>And therefore my brethren, conſider whether <note place="margin">Sect.</note> I ſpeake of mine own head, or whether I bring my minde, or the mind of God: If I ſpeake any other then y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> word of god, my reaſons ought not to moue you nor trouble you, but you ought to let the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> paſſe, as vaine &amp; friuolous: If I offer vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to you y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cell of god, you haue no cauſe to be angry, or to co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>plaine y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> we are too ſharp &amp; our iudgement is too hard: for would you that wee ſhould change y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> meaning of god, &amp; ſhould belie him? I haue vnderſtood y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>plaints &amp; the atte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtations y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ſom make, to cauſe vs to bethink our ſelues what we write of theſe matters. They ſay, &amp; it is true, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>trouerſie &amp; matter is not of the ſhadow of an Aſſe, or y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> wooll of a goate, (as the olde Prouerbe is) but of that they
<pb facs="tcp:4510:66"/> account moſt deare in this world, that is, of a thing for which we muſt forſake our countrie, our wife, our deare children, our goods, and all y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> euer wee may haue delight &amp; pleaſure in this worlde, yea to the looſing of our life, &amp; running ſtraight vpon death; and I denie not but theſe things are very ſharpe and hard to fleſh: where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore I cannot thinke therof without great com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſion of theſe, which are in ſuch a ſtraight: but what ſhoulde we doe there? wee ought to think it more ſtrange and fearefull to forſake Ieſus Chriſte, the heauenly habitation, and the eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall felicitie, then theſe tranſitorie thinges, which without that we muſt once forſake.</p>
            <p>Wee would gladly finde ſome way to ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port <note place="margin">Sect.</note> the infirmitie of fleſhe in this caſe, and to pleaſe it a litle in theſe great temptations. For it may be, if we were in the ſame danger, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther we ſhould be more weake &amp; fraile, more ſtrong &amp; conſtant, then thoſe whom we proue, God knoweth, who giueth ſtrength and co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie to whom it pleaſeth him, without whom we all are nothing: but I diſpute not nowe what conſtancie or inconſtancie might bee in mee or ſome other, &amp; what we ſhould do in ſuch a caſe: I diſpute what ought to be done in ſuch a caſe, &amp; what wee owe to God, as far as I can iudge by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſcriptures; for to flatter our ſelues, &amp; to lie
<pb facs="tcp:4510:66"/> againſt the truth of God, we ſhal gaine nothing: for all our coulours and excuſes, although they pleaſe our fleſhe, ſhall nothing auaile vs in the iudgement of God, if they haue no foundation in his worde, which wee muſt not corrupt and peruert to make it ſerue our affections, and to allowe our infirmitie and incredulitie as good.</p>
            <p>What then haue wee to do? Did not Nicho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demus goe to Ieſus Chriſte in the night? durſt <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Sect. Ioh.</hi> 3.</note> he confeſſe him publikely? is he therefore con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demned? As I cannot altogether excuſe Nicho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demus: as though he had not at y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> time ſome in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>credulitie and infirmitie in him, ſo I wiſhe that if wee haue not more faith and conſtancie then he, that we be not worſe, but at the leaſt like vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to him. Saint Iohn did not write in the commendation of the chiefe of Hieruſalem, that <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ioh.</hi> 2.</note> they did beleeue in Ieſus Chriſt, but that they durſt not confeſſe him, becauſe they feared to be caſt out of the Synagogue, and that they loued more the prayſe of men, then the praiſe of God. If Nichodemus went to Ieſus Chriſt by night, yet dyd hee not blaſpheme him, and denye hym by day. If at the firſt he confeſſed him not open<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, and maynteyned his cauſe publikely, yet did he not conſent to his death, nor ſuffered for <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Luk.</hi> 23. <hi>Ioh.</hi> 9. <hi>Ioh.</hi> 7.</note> his part that any ſhoulde doe hym harme or diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleaſure, but he alwayes maynteyned his cauſe
<pb facs="tcp:4510:67"/> in that he could: he declareth him ſelfe with Io<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeph of Arimathea to bee one of his diſciples, <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mat.</hi> 27. <hi>Luk.</hi> 13. <hi>Ioh.</hi> 19.</note> when all his diſciples forſooke him, hee made publike confeſſion of him in the greateſt danger he cold be in: And when hee had more cauſe of feare and offence then euer he had, they deman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded the body of Pilate to bury it.</p>
            <p>Woulde God that wee had many ſuch Ni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chodemians <note place="margin">Sect.</note> y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> wereſo feareful, that they would ſhewe them ſelues alwayes at neede: for they ſhould be more worthy prayſe, then a company of raſhe heads, which play the hardy men at the beginning, &amp; make great ſhewes, but they faile at neede, and for a thing of nothing denie and blaſpheme the Goſpel, and woulde not loſe one heire of their head for it: or then a company of wiſe men of the world, who will couer them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues with the example of Nichodemus: and in a counſell or company of aduerſaries, they durſt not open their mouth to vtter one word in fauour of the trueth: Nichodemus did farre o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe, howe fearefull ſoeuer he had been be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore: but theſe men will conſent rather to the death of the innocent, and if it be needfull, they wil condemne them themſelues, for feare of be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſuſpected. Neyther Nichodemus, nor Io<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeph of Arimathea woulde haue done that for their life, no not a good Pagan, which had anie
<pb facs="tcp:4510:67"/> loue to Iuſtice and equitie: yet is this the or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der of many which will arme themſelues with Nichodemus, but ſuch men might haue better occaſion to alleadge the example of Pilate in their behalf, &amp; to acco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>panie the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues with him: for they take more of him then of Nichodemus.</p>
            <p>So then, as I cannot condemne the true Nichodemians, although that fayth and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtancie <note place="margin">Sect.</note> is not ſuch in them, as it is to be requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red in a true Chriſtian: ſo can I not allowe thoſe, which in all thinges agree with the Ido<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laters, and renounce Ieſus Chriſt without any ſtay, and then wil excuſe and defend themſelues that it is lawfull for them, and that they doe not agaynſt the woorde of God: there is enough of one euil, without adding two. It ſufficeth once to haue blaſphemed Ieſus Chriſt, without blaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheming him againe, in affirming that blaſphe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mie is not blaſphemie, and in going about to induce others to blaſpheme him with vs, that we may haue mo companions with vs to couer our wickednes.</p>
            <p>Were it not rather the duetie of a good chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian, <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Sect. Pſal.</hi> 136. <hi>Exo.</hi> 16. <hi>Act.</hi> 15.</note> to confeſſe his infirmitie &amp; ſinne, &amp; weepe with y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> captiues of Babylon &amp; Egypt, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend his euill, and to lie vnto the ſpirite of God with Ananias and Sacharia? do wee not ſee the ſubtiltie of the fleſhe? whence commeth theſe
<pb facs="tcp:4510:68"/> delayes and excuſes, but of this fleſhe? which is ſo delicate, that it cannot ſuffer the thornes of Ieſus Chriſt, and ſo glorious, that it cannot ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer to be reprooued and condemned, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore muſt ſhee forge her ſelfe a newe Ieſus Chriſt, that hee may not diminiſhe any of her pleaſures and delights, nor her glory and arro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gancie, but may entertayne both the one and the other, with her carnall Ieſus Chriſt whiche he hath fayned to her ſelfe: for the fleſhe is alto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether contrary to Saint Paul, who will not glorie in any thing, but in the croſſe of Chriſte Ieſus, and in his tribulations and infirmities. But he abhorreth and deteſteth them: for ſhee hath not well noted the leſſon, that our Saui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our Chriſt gaue to his diſciples, as it hath been already ſayde, who ſo wyll be my diſciple, hee muſt carry his croſſe euery day and follow me: then he addeth a compariſon, to teach vs howe we ought to preferre our ſelues to his ſeruice, he inſtructeth vs to doe lyke a wyſe prince, who before he giue his defie vnto his enemye, and ioyne battayle with hym, hee examineth his force and riches, to knowe whether he be ſtrong enough to reſiſt him, to the intent he be not ſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med and confounded: if after he haue begonne, he be conſtrayned to leaue all and flye, or yeelde him ſelfe to his enemie: he wil alſo, that we take
<pb facs="tcp:4510:68"/> example of the wiſe builder, who before hee beginne his building, he reckoneth whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther hee ſhall haue money and ſtuffe enough to furniſhe him therein, that after he hath layd the foundation, he be not conſtrayned to ceaſe off, and to leaue his enterpryſe, and in the ende bee mocked.</p>
            <p>By this he giueth vs to vnderſtande, that yf <note place="margin">Sect.</note> wee will fight vnder his banner, and lay hande to the buylding of his houſe, wee muſt prepare our ſelues to worke, not to reſt, and to fight, not to ſleepe, and to receiue blowes, rather then be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefites: alſo he giueth vs to vnderſtande, that in beginning, wee muſt prepare our ſelues to go forwarde, and that we muſt not forſake his ban<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, nor our captaine when we heare the larom ſounded, and the aſſault is giuen, we muſt not doe like the cowardly Souldyers, who will kil all as they ſitte at table, but when they come to the buſineſſe to giue blowes, they are y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> firſt that fiye away, and cauſe others to be afrayd, and go hyde them ſelues. If we be truely faythfull, it is neceſſarie that we confeſſe Ieſus Chriſt ope<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, and that we die rather as the Prophets, Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles, and Martyres did, then to forſake him, and commit Idolatrie, ſuperſtition, or any acte that hath any appearance of it.</p>
            <p>If Ieſus Chriſt had once many ſuch cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pions,
<pb facs="tcp:4510:69"/> which would be prodigall of themſelues and liues, with ſo holy a prodigalitie, as they were, Antichriſt would ſoone be ouerthrowne, Ieſus Chriſt ſhoulde ſhortly raigne ouer al the earth, or death would diminiſhe and kill moe of our enemies, then the death of Sampſon killed of the Philiſtians: we ſee what happened in the <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iud.</hi> 27.</note> tymes of the Apoſtles and Martyrs; if they had been ſo daintie as we are, and had been ſo feare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full of their ſkinne, the religion of Chriſte had not been ſo much encreaſed in ſo ſmal a tyme: <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Luk.</hi> 18.</note> but it is harde eſpecially in our time, wherein faith almoſt faileth vpon earth, according to the propheſie of our Sauiour Chriſt, to finde men of ſuch fayth and conſtancie.</p>
            <p>What remedie is there then herein, if we can <note place="margin">Sect.</note> not come to this high degree, and to this chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an perſecution of the martyrs, and if wee dare not openly confeſſe Ieſus Chriſt with the dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger of our life, and wee feele not in our ſelues ſuch conſtancie to ſuffer death for his name; let vs come at the leaſt to the next degree, let vs be ſecret ſchollers with Nichodemus, and Ioſeph of Arimathea: And if we ſhewe not our ſelues ſo openly, yet at the leaſt, let vs do no diſhonour to Ieſus Chriſt, nor conſent vnto his aduerſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries in partaking at the table of diuels, &amp; if wee find our ſelues weaker the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Nichodemus, &amp; if we
<pb facs="tcp:4510:69"/> for feare of looſing our goods, our eſtimation &amp; liues, we be conſtrained too much to diſſemble, and to communicate with Idolaters; yet at the leaſt, let vs not iuſtifie, but conde<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ne our ſelues in y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> wherein we fayle, let vs acknowledge our ouer great infirmitie, &amp; the ouer burning loue that we beare to our ſelues, &amp; to the goods and dignities of this world, more the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to Ieſus Chriſt &amp; his word, let vs acknowledge in what euill &amp; bondage we are, let vs confeſſe that it is a pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment and iudgement of God vpon vs, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe of our ſinnes, as it was vpon the people of Iſrael in Egypt &amp; Babylon, let vs pray to God that he will encreaſe our faith to ouercome our infirmitie, and let vs confeſſe our faultes and ſinnes vnto him, and aſke him pardon and mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie for the ſame: let vs weepe and waile vnder this heauie burthen, and vnder this great tyran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie of Antichriſt which preſſeth vs ſo ſore: let vs aſke ayd, ſuccour, and deliuerance at his hands, rather then to excuſe and iuſtifie our ſelues, and ſo much to pleaſe our ſelues, and hee will ſee our teares, and heare our ſighes and grones, by which he wil be moued to pitie and compaſſion, for to deliuer and ſuccour vs, as he was moued by the like of the people of Iſrael.</p>
            <p>But in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> meane time, thoſe which remaine in <note place="margin">Sect.</note> ſuch miſerie, ſo ouerco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>e by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> infirmitie of their
<pb facs="tcp:4510:70"/> fleſhe, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> they are conſtrayned to communicate with idolaters, what excuſe can they haue, ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yng they knowe well they doe euill, doe they not ſinne againſt the holy Ghoſt? this is a que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion that ſome wil make, and a doubt that tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>menteth many conſciences: if al ſinnes, that we commit, knowing that wee do euill, were ſinne againſt the holy ghoſt, we ſhould commit fewe y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> were not ſin againſt y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> holy ghoſt: y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> adulterie &amp; murder of Dauid, and the denial, blaſphemy, and periurie of Saint Peter, ſhould bee ſinnes agaynſt the holy ghoſt, for they were not igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raunt that that was forbidde<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of God, but it is an other thing to ſinne of certayne malice, and in deſpite of God, and in contempt of his woorde, and to ſinne through ignoraunce, or through in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmitie of the fleſhe, which diſpleaſeth vs, and wee cannot ouercome it.</p>
            <p>But we muſt not ſo far ſtretch out this ſkinne <note place="margin">Sect.</note> of mans infirmitie, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> we wil wholly couer &amp; de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d our ſelues, &amp; by it giue our ſelues, to vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ſin is not ſinne: for in ſtead of leſſoning the ſinne, wee may aggrauate it, and may well make it irremiſſible, as the ſinne vnto death, for there is no great difference between the hypo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crites, &amp; the contemners and mockers of God, and betweene the blaſphemers, which ſinne a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the holy ghoſt; they are almoſt coſen ger<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mans:
<pb facs="tcp:4510:70"/> wee ſee alſo by experience that from one of the degrees man falleth into the other, for many of thoſe which become Atheiſtes and Epicures, and men without God, which haue at the firſt had ſome knowledge of the truth and nowe blaſpheme it, they are fallen into theſe pits by degrees: for they haue fayned to themſelues a Ieſus Chriſt after their owne fancie without amending their life, and with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any repentance, they haue dallied with him, and haue made it an art to blaſpheme him: wherefore they haue altogether loſt him, and God with him, whom without him we cannot haue: And therefore ſinne is no more to them ſinne, nor blaſphemie blaſphemie: for Ieſus Chriſt, is no more to them Ieſus Chriſt, nor God, to them God.</p>
            <p>Let vs learne to feare the Lord by others <note place="margin">Sect.</note> loſſe, and to flee ſuch curſe and fury of God: let vs beware that ſeeing Ieſus Chriſt hath driuen that wicked ſpirit out of our body, that, wherewith he threatneth the Iewes, befall not vnto vs, that is, that he returne not thither with ſeuen others woorſe then the firſt, and that the latter thinges be not worſe then the firſt, for it followeth not, if all ſinnes be not ſinnes vnto death, and as great and as wicked the one as the other, that yet they be not ſinnes ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent
<pb facs="tcp:4510:71"/> to bring vs to eternall damnation, if God of his mercy tooke not pitie of vs, and did par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don them vnto vs, let vs not thinke that wee are not bound to acknowledge and confeſſe them, and to pray euery day. O heauenly father forgiue vs our ſinnes, enter not into iudgement with thy ſeruant, reprooue vs not, nor correct vs in thine anger and furie, lead not vs into temptation, but deliuer vs from e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uill.</p>
            <p>I condemne not Dauid nor S. Peter as <note place="margin">Sect.</note> touching their perſons, nor the Iſraelites which worſhipped the Images of Nabucho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>donozer, in ſuch ſort as I condemne them for reprobates: but I allow not therfore y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> murder of Dauid, nor y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> denial of S. Peter, nor the ido<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latrie of the Iſraelites, but do condemne them as ſinnes, greeuous and greatly diſpleaſing to God, and worthy of eternall death, if God of his grace had not pardoned them. Yet becauſe the perſons acknowledged their faultes, and aſked him mercy for the ſame, their ſinne was not imputed vnto them: I haue alſo like hope that the Lord will take pitie and compaſſion on the poore, faythful, weake, and feareful, which are conſtrained to cary the yoke of An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tichriſt, and that he will ſtrengthen them more, ſo that they acknowledge themſelues weake,
<pb facs="tcp:4510:71"/> and ſinners as they are, and that they thinke not themſelues to be S. Paules, where they are not yet worthie to be accounted good Ni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>codemians, that they delight not themſelues in their errours, that they call not the table of Diuels the Supper of Ieſus Chriſt, but that they be grieued to be in that captiuitie, and to offend, and to ſee God dayly offended, that they auoyde idolatrie as much as they can, and that they hate and dereſt it with all their heart, without ſaying euil is good, or light is darke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes: for God curſeth ſuch men by his Prophet; but thoſe which eſteeme ſo much idolatrie, &amp; al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low it, and induce others thereto, they haue not well conſidered the wordes of the prophet, nor well thought of the malediction of God, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vnto they yeelde themſelues faultie.</p>
            <p>This is, wel beloued brethren, that which I <note place="margin">Sect.</note> would write vnto you at this time, not to trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble and torment further the poore, weake, and afflicted conſciences, but to abate the pride and preſumption of the fleſhe, and the proude, and fooliſh, which feele not their euil, but wil main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine it as good; hitherto tendeth my meaning that you may follow rather the councell of the ſpirit of God and his worde, then the councell of the fleſhe and worldly wiſdome. Wherefore I pray you take all in good parte, and conſider
<pb facs="tcp:4510:72"/> rather with what heart I write vnto you, the ſpeech of wordes. Thinke it not of arrogancie or preſumption, if I haue taken in hand to write vnto them whome I neuer ſawe, and which may be more perfect, and vnderſtande theſe things better then my ſelfe? For I haue not done it w<hi rend="sup">t</hi>out cauſe, but at y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> requeſt of many good men, which haue entreated me thereto, I done haue it alſo becauſe y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> many pore troubled conſciences haue often aſked councell of me in ſuch matters: and therefore I durſt not refuſe ſo iuſt and reaſonable a matter, ſeeing I am debtor to all my brethren; for I haue thought I might ſerue euery one which had neede of my inſtruction, and that in ſo doing I ſhoulde giue a teſtimonie of my fayth to others, which are more ſtrong and learned, and that I ſhould ſtirre them vp better to ſatiſfie ſuch queſtions and troubles in conſcience according to the grace that God hath giuen them, farre greater then to me, as alreadie ſome haue done long a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>goe, and may yet more amply, to whom I am not worthy to be compared; If alſo I cannot ſatiſfie all men, I ſhall nothing maruaile at it, but I ſhould maruaile at the contrary; for I know well my abilitie, and how hard the mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter is, further although I haue been tedious, yet haue I not taken in hand to write all that
<pb facs="tcp:4510:72"/> I might well ſay touching this matter, for it would require a more ample and eaſie treatiſe, but I haue indeuoured to touch generally the principall pointes, which firſt came to my minde, offring my ſelfe alwayes to bee readie to employ my ſelfe according to the talent that I haue receiued of God, to ſatiſfie you more at large, both in theſe &amp; al things elſe, wherein I may ſerue you, ſo farre as God ſhall giue mee grace: if my councell be a little ouer hard to the fleſh, thinke yet that it is faythfull, and ſuch as I would take for my ſelfe: if I woulde not goe againſt my owne conſcience according to the knowledge I haue receiued of the truth, wherevnto I had rather giue true and faithful witnes, then to lye vnto you and ſeduce you to pleaſe you, and to betray the truth of God: to whom you ſhall pray for me, and the Churche in theſe partes, euen as we pray for you beeing mindeful of your afflictions and perſeoutions, as if we were there our ſelues.</p>
            <p>In the meane time, my deare brethre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, walke <note place="margin">Sect.</note> in all feare and reuerence of God, in al humili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie of the ſpirit, and in all chriſtian modeſtie, wayting for your redemption: Let your light ſo ſhine before me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, that they may ſee your good workes, your heauenly father may be glorified, and that you may ſhut vp the mouthes of your
<pb facs="tcp:4510:73"/> aduerſaries: admoniſh one another with al ge<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tlenes, correct al blaſphemies, vices, &amp; imper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections, which raigne yet in the middeſt of vs, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> through you the name of God be not blaſphe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med amongſt the Infidels, call vpon God, and he will rayſe you vp, glorifie him, and he will glorifie you, humble your ſelues, and hee will exalt you, exhort one another, and waxe not cold, be not weary of wel doing reſiſt not thoſe that walke well, but ſupport the weake, enco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage them that faint, pricke them forward that ceaſe off, and thoſe that runne wel, that they may runne better, faynt not till you haue ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tayned the price, and the God of peace ſhall comfort you and ſtrengthen you to the ende, &amp; will not ſuffer you to be tempted further then you be able to beare: but will giue good iſſue, to all your temptations and troubles, to the glory of his holie name, and ſaluation of our owne ſoules: to whome onely bee all honour and glorye, nowe and for euer.</p>
            <closer>Amen.</closer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
